<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-25T16:29:56+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">salvaged.work</title><subtitle>A digital archive for salvaged analogue materials.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">La chevelure des choses</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/chevelure-des-choses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="La chevelure des choses" /><published>2022-02-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-02-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/chevelure-des-choses</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/chevelure-des-choses/"><![CDATA[<section>
	

<table id="infobox">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2">
                <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/front.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/front.jpg"></a>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2" id="infobox-subtitle"><cite>La chevelure des choses</cite></td>
        </tr>
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Authors</th>
            <td>Christian Dotremont &amp; Asger Jorn</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publisher</th>
            <td>Galerie Rive Gauche, Paris 1961</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Edition</th>
            <td>300 copies</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Dimensions</th>
            <td>27.1 x 21.4 cm, 32 pages</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
    </tbody>
</table>


	<p><strong>La chevelure des choses</strong> (The hair of things) is an exhibition catalogue by Belgian poet Christian Dotremont and Asger Jorn. The book is a catalogue from the pair's exhibition at Galerie Rive Gauche in Paris in 1961 and is a reproduction of small word drawings made by Jorn and Dotremont from 1948 to 1953, and also specifically from when the pair shared a room at the tuberculosis sanatorium in Silkeborg from November 1951 to February 1952. The catalogue contains a preface by Pierre Alechinsky and an original poem, <em>L'orthocatalographe</em> by Dotremont. Presented in a green stiff card slipcase, it was printed in Paris in 1961 by GIL.</p>
	
	<p>Jorn and Dotremont's collaboration on <em>La chevelure</em> relates to the pair's association with the Cobra, an experimental art movement active from 1948-1951 that focused on living creation and was a reaction to a perceived sterile and authoritarian atmosphere around modern art. Dotremont and Jorn were co-founders alongside Constant, Corneille, and Joseph Noiret. Their working method was based on spontaneity and experiment, and they drew their inspiration in particular from children’s drawings, from primitive art forms and from the work of Paul Klee and Joan Miró.<span class="footnote"><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COBRA_(art_movement)" target="_blank">COBRA (art movement). Wikipedia. Accessed 2022-02-05.</a></span></p>
	
	<p>Prior to the publication and exhibition of <em>La chevelure</em>, the pair collaborated on a word-painting in 1948 titled <em>Ici la chevelure des choses coiffée avec un doigt d'eau</em> (Here the hair of things capped with a finger of water).</p>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Texts</h2>
	
	<div class="collapsible-text-container">
<button class="collapsible-text-button">Preface (Pierre Alechinsky)</button>
<div class="collapsible-text-content">


<p>THE CAVES</p>

<p>What is it about? Of a healthy agitation. From the pillow to the stone, the holes of tuberculosis may be filled, the word cavern becomes a museum, it remains death. In medicine, in society, in language, everything is lived as if nothing were more difficult than to disappear.</p>

<p>Christian Dotremont and Asger Jorn have lived, have been living in a cave. But before being returned to normal life they scribbled these traces, grimaces, tender insults. Shrugs of shoulders and movements of panic? It is necessary to organize a little. For lack of applause or shouting, it was up to the feathered hands to find the new signs, and something to sink into.</p>

<p>These atheists’ ex-votos were wrapped up in a great laugh and tossed, in Brussels in 1949 and at the Silkeborg sanatorium in 1951, through the opening that leads to nothing (it being thought that nothing is already a formidable opening), while another agitation came to a standstill in Europe, and for good reason: Cobra. Readable paintings, visible words, here they are nevertheless gathered and offered in their state of project become memory, to the distracted eyes.</p>

<p>ALECHINSKY.</p>


</div>
</div>
	
	<div class="collapsible-text-container">
<button class="collapsible-text-button">L'orthocatalographe (Christian Dotremont)</button>
<div class="collapsible-text-content">
<div class="translation-toggle">
	<button class="translation-btn active" data-lang="original">Original</button>
	<button class="translation-btn" data-lang="english">English</button>
</div>
<div class="translatable-content">


<div class="original-text">
<strong>L'orthocatalographe</strong>

<p>
jamais je ne me rappelle j'appelle<br />
par son nom ce que j'interpelle<br />
jamais je ne me contiens je me contente<br />
de ce qui constamment me tente<br />
jamais je ne m'écorne ni l'œil ni l'oreille<br />
je vote contre les corbeaux pour les corneilles<br />
jamais je ne vais à la guerre<br />
j'orne mon cœur de ma colère<br />
jamais je ne donne de hennin à ma femme<br />
j'aime sa chevelure comme une flamme<br />
jamais je ne machine ni ne m'exquise<br />
je ne m'allèche que si me grise<br />
jamais je ne suis petit poucet<br />
dans la douce forêt du passé<br />
jamais je ne jette par la fenêtre<br />
le tas gitbont de rires ou est maêtre<br />
jamais je ne tombe dans la gueule du loup<br />
je ne tombe jamais dans la gueule du goût<br />
et je ne vais dans les musées que pour enlever les muselières.
</p>

<p>— Dotremont</p>
</div>

<div class="translated-text">
<strong>The Orthocatalograph</strong>

<p>
I never remember I call<br />
by its name what I call<br />
never I restrain myself I content myself<br />
with what constantly tempts me<br />
I never chip my eye or my ear<br />
I vote against the crows for the ravens<br />
I never go to war<br />
I adorn my heart with my anger<br />
I never give a henna to my wife<br />
I love her hair like a flame<br />
never I machine nor exquisite myself<br />
I do not lighten myself that if I get drunk<br />
never I am Tom Thumb<br />
in the sweet forest of the past<br />
never I throw by the window<br />
the heap of laughter where my being is<br />
never I fall in the mouth of the wolf<br />
I never fall into the mouth of the taste<br />
and I go to the museums only to remove the muzzles.
</p>

<p>— Dotremont</p>

<p><em>(Translated with DeepL)</em></p>
</div>

</div>
</div>
</div>


	
	<script>
var coll = document.getElementsByClassName("collapsible-text-button");
var i;

for (i = 0; i < coll.length; i++) {
  coll[i].addEventListener("click", function() {
    this.classList.toggle("active");
    var container = this.parentElement;
    var content = this.nextElementSibling;
    if (content.style.maxHeight){
      content.style.maxHeight = null;
      container.classList.remove("expanded");
    } else {
      container.classList.add("expanded");
      content.style.maxHeight = content.scrollHeight + "px";
    } 
  });
}
</script>

	
	<h3>Explore the Catalogue</h3>
	
	<iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/chevelure-des-choses" width="100%" height="500" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen></iframe>
	
	<p><em>This is a preview only - <a href="https://archive.org/details/chevelure-des-choses" target="_blank">view fullsize on archive.org</a></em></p>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Gallery</h2>
	
	<section
		data-featherlight-gallery
		data-featherlight-filter="a"
		class="gallery-grid"
		>
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/chevelure_painting.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/chevelure_painting.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption><em>Ici la chevelure des choses coiffée avec un doigt d'eau</em> (Here the hair of things capped with a finger of water), a 1948 word painting by Jorn and Dotremont.</figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/chevelure_01.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/chevelure_01.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption></figcaption>
			</figure>
		
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/chevelure_02.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/chevelure_02.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption></figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/chevelure_03.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/chevelure_03.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption></figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/chevelure_04.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/chevelure-des-choses/chevelure_04.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption></figcaption>
			</figure>
	</section>
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(The hair of things) is an exhibition catalogue by Belgian poet Christian Dotremont and Asger Jorn.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mémoires</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/memoires/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mémoires" /><published>2022-02-03T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-02-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/memoires</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/memoires/"><![CDATA[<section>
	<table id="infobox">
		<tbody>
			<tr>
				<td colspan="2">
					<a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/memoires/front.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/memoires/front.jpg"></a>
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<th scope="row">Authors</th>
				<td>Guy Debord &amp; Asger Jorn</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<th scope="row">Publisher</th>
				<td>Permild &amp; Rosengreen, Copenhagen</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<th scope="row">Publishing date</th>
				<td>1959</td>
			</tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
	
	<p><strong>Mémoires</strong> is an artist's book made by the Danish artist Asger Jorn in collaboration with the French artist and theorist Guy Debord.<p>
	
	<p>Jorn collaborated with Debord on two art books, the first being <em>Fin de Copenhague</em> in 1957, during their time as members of Situationist International. The book makes use of psychogeography, a concept close to Debord which made use of the exploration of urban environments and the emphasis of interpersonal connections to places and arbitrary routes. While the book was credited to Debord, Jorn contributed with <em>structures portantes</em> (load-bearing structures) in the form of ink splashes.</p>
	
	<p><em>Mémoires</em> consists of three sections, each separated by a page containing a date and a quote:</p>
	<ul>
		<li>June 1952, with a quote from Karl Marx. <em>&quot;Let the dead bury the dead, and mourn them.... our fate will be to become the first living people to enter the new life.&quot;</em></li>
		<li>December 1952, with a quote from Johan Huizinga's <em>The Decline of the Middle Ages</em></li>
		<li>September 1953, with a quote from Soubise in a letter to Choiseul.</li>
	</ul>
	
	<div class="quote">
	<p>The work contains two separate layers. The first is printed with black ink, reproducing found text and graphics taken from newspapers and magazines. The second layer is printed using coloured inks, splashed across the pages. These sometimes connect images and text, sometimes cover them, and sometimes are seemingly unconnected. The black layer contains fragments of text, maps of Paris and London, illustrations of siege warfare, cheap reproductions of old masters and questions such as 'How do you feel about the world at the moment, Sir?' The coloured layer contains freefloating ink splashes, lines created by a matchstick loaded in ink, and a Rorschach inkblob.</p>

	<p>Other pages deal with more personal themes, including a cartoon of the first showing of his film Hurlements en Faveur de Sade, with comments for and against, and references to Dérive, which would become known as Situationist Drift, the habit of walking aimlessly through a city in an attempt to find its spirit. Détournement ('diversion' or 'disruption') is also employed in the book to disorient the reader by creating startling collaged juxtapositions. Originally deriving from Dada,[2] détournement would become a key situationist strategy.</p>

	<p>The last page is an orange swirl, above which reads the single sentence <em>'I wanted to speak the beautiful language of my century.'</em></p>
	<p class="quote-attrib">- Wikipedia, Mémoires</p>
	</div>
	
	<p>The book is furnished with a sandpaper cover after a suggestion made by the printer, V. O. Permild. Jorn had asked for an unconventional material as a book cover.</p>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Explore the Book</h2>
	
	<iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/memoires-jorn-debord" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen></iframe>
	
	<em>This is a preview only - <a href="https://archive.org/details/memoires-jorn-debord" target="_blank">view fullsize on archive.org</a></em> 
	</section>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Gallery</h2>
	
	<section
		data-featherlight-gallery
		data-featherlight-filter="a"
		class="gallery-grid"
		>
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/memoires/memoires_01.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/memoires/memoires_01.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption></figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/memoires/memoires_02.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/memoires/memoires_02.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption></figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/memoires/memoires_03.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/memoires/memoires_03.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption></figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/memoires/memoires_04.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/memoires/memoires_04.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption></figcaption>
			</figure>
	</section>
</section>

<ul>
	<li>Wikipedia, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C3%A9moires" target="_blank">Mémoires</a>. Accessed 2022-02-03.</li>
</ul>

<script>
var coll = document.getElementsByClassName("collapsible-text-button");
var i;

for (i = 0; i < coll.length; i++) {
  coll[i].addEventListener("click", function() {
    this.classList.toggle("active");
    var container = this.parentElement;
    var content = this.nextElementSibling;
    if (content.style.maxHeight){
      content.style.maxHeight = null;
      container.classList.remove("expanded");
    } else {
      container.classList.add("expanded");
      content.style.maxHeight = content.scrollHeight + "px";
    } 
  });
}
</script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[is an artist's book made by the Danish artist Asger Jorn in collaboration with the French artist and theorist Guy Debord.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Asger Jorn Catalogue raisonné Series</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/jorn-catalogue-raisonne/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Asger Jorn Catalogue raisonné Series" /><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/jorn-catalogue-raisonne</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/jorn-catalogue-raisonne/"><![CDATA[<section>
	

<table id="infobox">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2">
                <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-scandinavia/front.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-scandinavia/front.jpg"></a>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2" id="infobox-subtitle"><cite>Asger Jorn Catalogue raisonné Series</cite></td>
        </tr>
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Authors</th>
            <td>Guy Atkins &amp; Troels Andersen</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publisher</th>
            <td>Lund Humphries Publishers Ltd./Borgens Forlag</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publishing date</th>
            <td>1968-2006</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
    </tbody>
</table>

	
	<p><strong>Asger Jorn Catalogue raisonné Series</strong> is a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.<p>
	
	<div class="quote">
	<p>This is a detailed study of the early career of the Danish artist, Asger Jorn, who is one of the most versatile and original artists at work in Europe today. His output, besides oils and acrylics, includes many other media: ceramics, graphics, drawings, tapestries, and book illustrations. He is also a prolific writer on a great variety of subjects.</p>

	<p>This is not only a pioneer work of reference for the study of Asger Jorn, but it also contains vital source material for assessing the modern Danish art movement as a whole. The latter is important for its own sake, as well as for the decisive influence which some of the leading Danish artists had upon COBRA.</p>
	<p class="quote-attrib">- Guy Atkins, Jorn in Scandinavia 1930-1953, jacket inner leaf</p>
	</div>
	
	<p>Guy Atkins met Jorn in 1956 when the artist visited London for the first time. By 1961 they had become close friends and they decided in the spring of that year, during lunch one day at the Coupole in Paris, that it would be interesting and worth-while to try and trace the whereabouts of Jorn's early paintings. Many of these were neither signed not dated and had disappeared without trace. As the artist wrote in the preface to the first volume of the œuvre catalogue 'The idea of undertaking the huge task of searching for these early and missing pictures came from Guy Atkins, who carried the job through on his own initiative from start to finish.'</p>
	
	<p>Unfortunately the artist did not live to see the completion of the task, since volumes 2 and 3 only appeared after his death.</p>
	<p class="quote-attrib">- Guy Atkins, Asger Jorn - The Final Years 1965-1973, jacket inner leaf</p>
	</div>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Explore the Books</h2>
	
	<p>Click on the covers to visit the individual article pages for each book:</p>
	
	<section
		class="gallery-grid"
		>
			<figure>
				<a href="/article/atkins-jorn-scandinavia"><img src="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-scandinavia/front.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Jorn in Scandinavia 1930-1953</figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/article/atkins-jorn-crucial-years"><img src="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-crucial-years/front.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Asger Jorn - The Crucial Years 1954-1964</figcaption>
			</figure>
		
			<figure>
				<a href="/article/atkins-jorn-final-years"><img src="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-final-years/front.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Asger Jorn - The Final Years 1965-1973</figcaption>
			</figure>
		
			<figure>
				<a href="/article/atkins-jorn-supplement"><img src="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-supplement/front.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Asger Jorn - Supplement - Paintings 1930-1973</figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/article/atkins-jorn-revised-supplement"><img src="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-revised-supplement/front.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Asger Jorn - Revised Supplement</figcaption>
			</figure>
	</section>
</section>

<script>
var coll = document.getElementsByClassName("collapsible-text-button");
var i;

for (i = 0; i < coll.length; i++) {
  coll[i].addEventListener("click", function() {
    this.classList.toggle("active");
    var container = this.parentElement;
    var content = this.nextElementSibling;
    if (content.style.maxHeight){
      content.style.maxHeight = null;
      container.classList.remove("expanded");
    } else {
      container.classList.add("expanded");
      content.style.maxHeight = content.scrollHeight + "px";
    } 
  });
}
</script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[is a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Asger Jorn - Supplement - Paintings 1930-1973</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-supplement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Asger Jorn - Supplement - Paintings 1930-1973" /><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-supplement</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-supplement/"><![CDATA[<section>
	

<table id="infobox">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2">
                <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-supplement/front.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-supplement/front.jpg"></a>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2" id="infobox-subtitle"><cite>Asger Jorn: Supplement - Paintings 1930-1973</cite></td>
        </tr>
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Authors</th>
            <td>Guy Atkins &amp; Troels Andersen</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publisher</th>
            <td>Lund Humphries Publishers Ltd.</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publishing date</th>
            <td>1986</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Series</th>
            <td>Asger Jorn Catalogue raisonné</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Followed by</th>
            <td>Asger Jorn - Revised Supplement</td>
        </tr>
        
        
    </tbody>
</table>

	
	<p><strong>Asger Jorn - Supplement - Paintings 1930-1973</strong> is the penultimate book in a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.<p>
	
	<div class="quote">
	<p>This supplement to the œuvre catalogue of Asger Jorn’s paintings contains new descriptions of pictures that have come to light since the publication of Asger Jorn: the final years in 1980. In addition to these new discoveries, all the entries that were contained in the appendixes to the three volumes have also been included. Both groups of pictures are now integrated and placed in a single chronological order.</p>
	<p class="quote-attrib">- Guy Atkins, Asger Jorn - Supplement - Paintings 1930-1973</p>
	</div>
</section>

<section>
	<h3>Contents</h3>
	<p>Part One</p>
	<ol>
		<li>Pierre Alechinsky</li>
		<li>Guy Atkins</li>
		<li>Jean Dubuffet</li>
		<li>Werner Haftmann</li>
		<li>Wilfredo Lam</li>
		<li>Conroy Maddox</li>
		<li>Matta</li>
		<li>Karl Schawelka</li>
		<li>Illustrations in large format</li>
	</ol>
	<p>Part Two</p>
	<ul>
		<li>The Supplement &amp; Addenda</li>
	</ul>
	<p>Part Three</p>
	<ul>
		<li>Dis-authentications, omissions, additions and corrections</li>
	</ul>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Explore the Book</h2>
	
	<iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/jorn-supplement-paintings" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen></iframe>
		
	<p><em>This is a preview only - <a href="https://archive.org/details/jorn-supplement-paintings" target="_blank">view fullsize on archive.org</a></em></p>
</section>

<script>
var coll = document.getElementsByClassName("collapsible-text-button");
var i;

for (i = 0; i < coll.length; i++) {
  coll[i].addEventListener("click", function() {
    this.classList.toggle("active");
    var container = this.parentElement;
    var content = this.nextElementSibling;
    if (content.style.maxHeight){
      content.style.maxHeight = null;
      container.classList.remove("expanded");
    } else {
      container.classList.add("expanded");
      content.style.maxHeight = content.scrollHeight + "px";
    } 
  });
}
</script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[is the penultimate book in a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Jorn in Scandinavia 1930-1953</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-scandinavia/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jorn in Scandinavia 1930-1953" /><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-scandinavia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-scandinavia/"><![CDATA[<section>
	

<table id="infobox">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2">
                <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-scandinavia/front.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-scandinavia/front.jpg"></a>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2" id="infobox-subtitle"><cite>Jorn in Scandinavia 1930-1953</cite></td>
        </tr>
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Authors</th>
            <td>Guy Atkins &amp; Troels Andersen</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publisher</th>
            <td>Percy Lund, Humphries &amp; Co. Ltd./Borgens Forlag</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publishing date</th>
            <td>1968</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Series</th>
            <td>Asger Jorn Catalogue raisonné</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Followed by</th>
            <td>Asger Jorn - The Crucial Years 1954-1964</td>
        </tr>
        
        
    </tbody>
</table>

	
	<p><strong>Jorn in Scandinavia 1930-1953</strong> is the first book in a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.<p>
	
	<div class="quote">
	<p>The author has traced Asger Jorn's artistic development from its beginnings around 1930 to the completion of the 'Silent Myth' cycle in 1953. This group of paintings forms a climax, coming at the end of a very rigorous and prolonged self-imposed apprenticeship, which had lasted twenty-three years. During this period the artist lived in Denmark, though he made numerous trips abroad: to Sweden, Western Europe, and once for six months to Tunisia. In the autumn of 1953 he decided to leave Scandinavia, and this decision proved to be an important turning-point for his art. Since 1953 he has worked mostly in Paris and Albisola, Italy.</p>
	
	<p>Part One examines the various stylistic landmarks of the artist's development, for example his very personal and lyrical series of 'Didaska' paintings and water-colours from the middle 'forties; the 'word pictures' made together with the Belgian poet, Christian Dotremont, at the time of the COBRA movement; the humorous and yet strangely obsessional 'Aganak' sketches of imaginary beasts, which date from a year of extreme poverty and suffering, shortly before the artist underwent a long hospital cure for tuberculosis.</p>
	
	<p>Part Two includes all the paintings by Jorn which it has been possible to discover, dating from 1930 up to the winter of 1953/4. They amount to 855, with a few extra works listed in an appendix. Illustrations accompany the descriptions in practically every case and most of the photographs were commissioned specially for the catalogue.</p>
	<p class="quote-attrib">- Guy Atkins, Jorn in Scandinavia 1930-1953, jacket inner leaf</p>
	</div>
</section>

<section>
	<h3>Contents</h3>
	<p>Part One</p>
	<ol>
		<li>Themes and Styles</li>
			<ul>
				<li>From naturalism to the influence of Paris (1930-1939)</li>
				<li>Small things (1940-1941)</li>
				<li>Didaska (1944-1945)</li>
				<li>Saxnäs (1946)</li>
				<li>Tunisian paintings (1947-1948)</li>
				<li>Word pictures with Christian Dotremont (1948-1953)</li>
				<li>Le droit de l'aigle (1949-1950)</li>
				<li>Historical pictures (1949-1950)</li>
				<li>Aganaks (1950-1951)</li>
				<li>The Seasons (1948-1953)</li>
				<li>From COBRA to the Silent Myth (1948-1953)</li>
				<li>Murals</li>
			</ul>
		<li>Historical Background</li>
		<li>Collections</li>
		<li>Description and Identification of the Paintings</li>
	</ol>
	<p>Part Two</p>
	<ul>
		<li>Catalogue of paintings from 1930 to 1953/4</li>
		<li>Appendix, Bibliography, Credits, Index</li>
	</ul>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Explore the Book</h2>
	
	<iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/jorn-scandinavia" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen></iframe>
		
	<p><em>This is a preview only - <a href="https://archive.org/details/atkins-jorn-scandinavia" target="_blank">view fullsize on archive.org</a></em></p>
</section>

<script>
var coll = document.getElementsByClassName("collapsible-text-button");
var i;

for (i = 0; i < coll.length; i++) {
  coll[i].addEventListener("click", function() {
    this.classList.toggle("active");
    var container = this.parentElement;
    var content = this.nextElementSibling;
    if (content.style.maxHeight){
      content.style.maxHeight = null;
      container.classList.remove("expanded");
    } else {
      container.classList.add("expanded");
      content.style.maxHeight = content.scrollHeight + "px";
    } 
  });
}
</script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[is the first book in a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Asger Jorn - Revised Supplement</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-revised-supplement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Asger Jorn - Revised Supplement" /><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-revised-supplement</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-revised-supplement/"><![CDATA[<section>
	

<table id="infobox">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2">
                <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-revised-supplement/front.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-revised-supplement/front.jpg"></a>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2" id="infobox-subtitle"><cite>Asger Jorn: Revised Supplement</cite></td>
        </tr>
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Authors</th>
            <td>Guy Atkins &amp; Troels Andersen</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publisher</th>
            <td>Lund Humphries Publishers Ltd.</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publishing date</th>
            <td>2006</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Series</th>
            <td>Asger Jorn Catalogue raisonné</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
    </tbody>
</table>

	
	<p><strong>Asger Jorn - Revised Supplement</strong> is the final book in a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.<p>
	
	<div class="quote">
	<p>The first supplement to the œuvre catalogue of Asger Jorn’s oil paintings appeared in 1986. It described one hundred paintings that had been discovered since the appearance of the third volume of the oeuvre catalogue Asger Jorn: the final years six years earlier. In addition, all entries from the appendixes of the preceding three volumes of the catalogue were included.</p>

	<p>Thanks to the cooperation of a number of European and American institutions and private persons we have in the past twenty years been able to identify a further 123 oil paintings. In view of the growing number of untenable attributions, all precautions have been taken to secure reliable information about the provenance and history of the paintings included in the present edition. In some cases a technical investigation has also taken place.</p>

	<p>In recent years very few authentic paintings have emerged. We have therefore now decided to publish the revised supplement, and to consider the registration of Asger Jorn’s oil paintings - spanning a period of 45 years of research - concluded.</p>
	<p class="quote-attrib">- Troels Andersen, Asger Jorn - Revised Supplement</p>
	</div>
</section>

<section>
	<h3>Contents</h3>
	<p>Part One</p>
	<ol>
		<li>An interview with Pola Gauguin</li>
		<li>Öyvind Fahlström on Jorn</li>
		<li>An interview with Jacques Michel</li>
		<li>Illustrations in large format</li>
	</ol>
	<p>Part Two</p>
	<ul>
		<li>The Supplement</li>
	</ul>
	<p>Part Three</p>
	<ul>
		<li>Dis-authentications, omissions, additions and corrections</li>
	</ul>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Explore the Book</h2>
	
	<iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/jorn-revised-supplement" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen></iframe>
		
	<p><em>This is a preview only - <a href="https://archive.org/details/jorn-revised-supplement" target="_blank">view fullsize on archive.org</a></em></p>
</section>

<script>
var coll = document.getElementsByClassName("collapsible-text-button");
var i;

for (i = 0; i < coll.length; i++) {
  coll[i].addEventListener("click", function() {
    this.classList.toggle("active");
    var container = this.parentElement;
    var content = this.nextElementSibling;
    if (content.style.maxHeight){
      content.style.maxHeight = null;
      container.classList.remove("expanded");
    } else {
      container.classList.add("expanded");
      content.style.maxHeight = content.scrollHeight + "px";
    } 
  });
}
</script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[is the final book in a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Asger Jorn - The Final Years 1965-1973</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-final-years/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Asger Jorn - The Final Years 1965-1973" /><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-final-years</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-final-years/"><![CDATA[<section>
	

<table id="infobox">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2">
                <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-final-years/front.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-final-years/front.jpg"></a>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2" id="infobox-subtitle"><cite>Asger Jorn: The Final Years 1965-1973</cite></td>
        </tr>
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Authors</th>
            <td>Guy Atkins &amp; Troels Andersen</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publisher</th>
            <td>Lund Humphries Publishers Ltd./Borgens Forlag</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publishing date</th>
            <td>1980</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Series</th>
            <td>Asger Jorn Catalogue raisonné</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Followed by</th>
            <td>Asger Jorn - Supplement - Paintings 1930-1973</td>
        </tr>
        
        
    </tbody>
</table>

	
	<p><strong>Asger Jorn - The Final Years 1965-1973</strong> is the third book in a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.<p>
	
	<div class="quote">
	<p>The two most important creative phases described in the present volume both occurred near the end of Jorn’s life. The year 1970 saw a renewal of his serious and almost exclusive dedication to painting - after the distractions of the previous years. The result of this newly found concentration was a sequence of works of the highest order, comparable in quality with those of the mid- to late 1950s.</p>

	<p>In 1972 Jorn turned, for the first time, to sculpture in bronze and marble. His major achievement as a sculptor during this short but important period is described by Ursula Lehmann-Brockhaus in Chapter 4.</p>
	
	<p>By including chapters, contributed by Frank Whitford, on acrylics and collages, a large part of Jorn’s œuvre (in its astonishing variety) has now been sketched out - bearing in mind the chapters on ceramics, graphics and tapestries in the preceding volume.</p>
	<p class="quote-attrib">- Guy Atkins, Asger Jorn - The Final Years 1965-1973</p>
	</div>
</section>

<section>
	<h3>Contents</h3>
	<p>Part One</p>
	<ol>
		<li>The final years</li>
		<li>Acrylics by Frank Whitford</li>
		<li>Collages and décollages by Frank Whitford</li>
		<li>Sculpture by Ursula Lehmann-Brockhaus</li>
		<li>Forgeries</li>
	</ol>
	<p>Part Two</p>
	<ul>
		<li>Appendix to the catalogue of paintings from 1934-73</li>
		<li>Bibliography</li>
	</ul>
	
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Explore the Book</h2>
	
	<iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/jorn-final-years" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen></iframe>
		
	<p><em>This is a preview only - <a href="https://archive.org/details/jorn-final-years" target="_blank">view fullsize on archive.org</a></em></p>
</section>

<script>
var coll = document.getElementsByClassName("collapsible-text-button");
var i;

for (i = 0; i < coll.length; i++) {
  coll[i].addEventListener("click", function() {
    this.classList.toggle("active");
    var container = this.parentElement;
    var content = this.nextElementSibling;
    if (content.style.maxHeight){
      content.style.maxHeight = null;
      container.classList.remove("expanded");
    } else {
      container.classList.add("expanded");
      content.style.maxHeight = content.scrollHeight + "px";
    } 
  });
}
</script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[is the third book in a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Asger Jorn - The Crucial Years 1954-1964</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-crucial-years/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Asger Jorn - The Crucial Years 1954-1964" /><published>2021-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-crucial-years</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/atkins-jorn-crucial-years/"><![CDATA[<section>
	

<table id="infobox">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2">
                <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-crucial-years/front.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/atkins-jorn-crucial-years/front.jpg"></a>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2" id="infobox-subtitle"><cite>Asger Jorn: The Crucial Years 1954-1964</cite></td>
        </tr>
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Authors</th>
            <td>Guy Atkins &amp; Troels Andersen</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publisher</th>
            <td>Lund Humphries Publishers Ltd.</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publishing date</th>
            <td>1977</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Series</th>
            <td>Asger Jorn Catalogue raisonné</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Followed by</th>
            <td>Asger Jorn - The Final Years 1965-1973</td>
        </tr>
        
        
    </tbody>
</table>

	
	<p><strong>Asger Jorn - The Crucial Years 1954-1964</strong> is the second book in a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.<p>
	
	<div class="quote">
	<p>The years 1954 to 1964 were ‘crucial years’ for they saw the emergence of Jorn as a major figure in European art. In 1958, at Expo in Brussels, his work held its own alongside paintings by other leading artists. The following year he made a huge and magnificent ceramic mural, 10 x 88 ft, for a building in Aarhus.</p>
	
	<p>Artistic recognition inevitably brought commercial pressures, against which Jorn found it necessary to defend himself. In 1959 he painted a series of pictures which he hoped would be rejected by the public. His so-called <em>Modifications</em> consisted of sentimental old canvases bought in junk shops and overpainted or ‘modernized’. These pictures did not, in fact, find buyers at the time. But his London exhibition of equally un-Jornlike ‘luxury’ paintings in 1961 was an unexpected sell-out.</p>
	
	<p>Part Two contains information on Jorn’s dealers and collectors, and a chapter on the large number of forgeries which began to appear on the art market after Jorn’s death... Part Three includes the illustrated oeuvre catalogue of 751 paintings from the period, as well as an appendix relating to earlier pictures which came to light too late for inclusion in the previous volume. A feature of special interest to art historians is the bibliography of 513 entries, listing public and private collections, exhibitions, auctions, books and articles.</p>
	<p class="quote-attrib">- Guy Atkins, Asger Jorn - The Crucial Years 1954-1964, jacket inner leaf</p>
	</div>
</section>

<section>
	<h3>Contents</h3>
	<p>Part One</p>
	<ol>
		<li>Switzerland and Italy (1953-5)</li>
		<li>Breakthrough (1956-8)</li>
		<li>Stalingrad: No Man’s Land (1956-72)</li>
		<li>Situationists (1957—61)</li>
		<li>Modifications and Disfigurations (1959-62)</li>
		<li>Luxury paintings and after (1961-4)</li>
		<li>Ceramics by Erik Nyholm</li>
		<li>Graphics by Ursula Lehmann-Brockhaus née Schmitt</li>
		<li>Tapestries by Pierre Wemaëre</li>
		<li>Writings</li>
	</ol>
	<p>Part Two</p>
	<ul>
		<li>Dealers and collectors</li>
		<li>Titles of paintings</li>
		<li>Forgeries</li>
	</ul>
	<p>Part Three</p>
	<ul>
		<li>Bibliography</li>
	</ul>
	
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Explore the Book</h2>
	
	<iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/jorn-crucial-years" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen></iframe>
		
	<p><em>This is a preview only - <a href="https://archive.org/details/jorn-crucial-years" target="_blank">view fullsize on archive.org</a></em></p>
</section>

<script>
var coll = document.getElementsByClassName("collapsible-text-button");
var i;

for (i = 0; i < coll.length; i++) {
  coll[i].addEventListener("click", function() {
    this.classList.toggle("active");
    var container = this.parentElement;
    var content = this.nextElementSibling;
    if (content.style.maxHeight){
      content.style.maxHeight = null;
      container.classList.remove("expanded");
    } else {
      container.classList.add("expanded");
      content.style.maxHeight = content.scrollHeight + "px";
    } 
  });
}
</script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[is the second book in a five-volume catalogue raisonné series on the Danish painter Asger Jorn by Guy Atkins and Troels Andersen.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cybernetic Serendipity - The Computer and the Arts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/cybernetic-serendipity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cybernetic Serendipity - The Computer and the Arts" /><published>2021-06-11T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-08-05T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/cybernetic-serendipity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/cybernetic-serendipity/"><![CDATA[<section>
	

<table id="infobox">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2">
                <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/front.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/front.jpg"></a>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2" id="infobox-subtitle"><cite>Cybernetic Serendipity: The Computer and the Arts</cite></td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Editor</th>
            <td>Jasia Reichardt</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Exhibition Staff</th>
            <td>Jasia Reichardt, Mark Dowson, Peter Schmidt, Franciszka Themerson</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publisher</th>
            <td>Studio International, London</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publishing date</th>
            <td>July 1968 (1st edition)</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
    </tbody>
</table>


	<p><strong>Cybernetic Serendipity - The Computer and the Arts</strong> is the title of a special 1968 issue of the British magazine 'Studio International.' The issue was first published to coincide with an exhibition entitled 'Cybernetic Serendipity,' dealing broadly with the demonstration of how humans can use the computer and new technology to extend creativity and inventiveness.<p>
	
	<p>The exhibition was held at the Institute of Contemporary Arts in London from August 2 to October 20, 1968. The exhibition was organized by Jasia Reichardt in collaboration with Mark Dowson (technological adviser) and Peter Schmidt (musical adviser). The exhibition was designed by Franciszka Themerson.</p>
</section>

<section>
	<h2 class="header-nestled">Exhibition</h2>
	

<div class="thumbnail-container">
    <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/exhibition.jpg"><img class="thumbnail-image" src="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/exhibition.jpg"></a>
    
    <div class="thumbnail-caption">View of the exhbition.</div>
    
</div>

	
	

<div class="thumbnail-container">
    <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/ihnatowicz_sound_activated_mobile.jpg"><img class="thumbnail-image" src="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/ihnatowicz_sound_activated_mobile.jpg"></a>
    
    <div class="thumbnail-caption">Edward Ihnatowicz's <em>Sound Activated Mobile (SAM)</em>, which was also featured in the exhibition catalogue.</div>
    
</div>

	
	<p>The <em>Cybernetic Serendipity</em> exhibition represented three areas of the relationship between technology and creativity:</p>
	
	<ul>
		<li>Computer-generated graphics, computer-animated films, computer-composed and -played music, and computer poems and texts</li>
		<li>Cybernetic devices as works of art, cybernetic environments, remote-control robots and painting machines</li>
		<li>Machines demonstrating the uses of computers and an environment dealing with the history of cybernetics</li>
	</ul>
	
	<p>A number of recognised academics, scientists, artists, and composers took part in the exhibition, including Max Bense, Nicholas Negroponte, Earle Brown, John Cage, Nam June Paik, Karlheinz Stockhausen, Jean Tinguely, Iannis Xenakis, and Peter Zinovieff.</p>
	
	<div class="quote">
	<p>The idea behind this venture... is to show some of the creative forms engendered by technology. The aim is to present an area of activity which manifests artists' involvement with science, and the scientists' involvement with the arts; also, to show the links between the random systems employed by artists, composers and poets, and those involved with the making and the use of cybernetic devices.</p>
	
	<p>Cybernetic Serendipity deals with possibilities rather than achievements... [t]here are no heroic claims to be made because computers have so far neither revolutionized music, nor art, nor poetry, in the same way that they have revolutionized science.</p>
	
	<p>...no visitor to the exhibition, unless he reads all the notes relating to all the works, will know whether he is looking at something made by an artist, engineer. mathematician, or architect. Nor is it particularly im portant to know the background of the makers of the various robots, machines and graphics-it will not alter their impact, although it might make us see them differently.</p>
	
	<p class="quote-attrib">- Introduction by Jasia Reichardt, exhibition catalogue</p>
	</div>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Exhibition Catalogue</h2>
	
	<p>Numbering just over 100 pages, the <em>Cybernetic Serendipity</em> exhibition catalogue contains contributions from cybernetics originator Norbert Wiener, musicians Karlheinz Stockhausen and John Cage, and a range of individuals involved in the cybernetic movement, including photographic and written documentation of many different artistic, architectural, and musical creations.</p>
	
	<h3>Selected Essays</h3>
	
	<div class="collapsible-text-container">
<button class="collapsible-text-button">Introduction (Jasia Reichardt)</button>
<div class="collapsible-text-content">


<p>Cybernetic Serendipity is an international exhibition exploring and demonstrating some of the relationships between technology and creativity.</p>

<p>The idea behind this venture, for which I am grateful to Professor Max Bense of Stuttgart, is to show some of the creative forms engendered by technology. The aim is to present an area of activity which manifests artists’ involvement with science, and the scientists’ involvement with the arts; also, to show the links between the random systems employed by artists, composers and poets, and those involved with the making and the use of cybernetic devices.</p>

<p>The exhibition is divided into three sections, and these sections are represented in the catalogue in a different order:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Computer-generated graphics, computer-animated films, computer-composed and -played music, and computer poems and texts</li>
  <li>Cybernetic devices as works of art, cybernetic environments, remote-control robots and painting machines</li>
  <li>Machines demonstrating the uses of computers and an environment dealing with the history of cybernetics.</li>
</ol>

<p>Cybernetic Serendipity deals with possibilities rather than achievements, and in this sense it is prematurely optimistic. There are no heroic claims to be made because computers have so far neither revolutionized music, nor art, nor poetry, in the same way that they have revolutionized science.</p>

<p>There are two main points which make this exhibition and this catalogue unusual in the contexts in which art exhibitions and catalogues are normally seen. The first is that no visitor to the exhibition, unless he reads all the notes relating to all the works, will know whether he is looking at something made by an artist, engineer. mathematician, or architect. Nor is it particularly im portant to know the background of the makers of the various robots, machines and graphics-it will not alter their impact, although it might make us see them differently.</p>

<p>The other point is more significant.</p>

<p>New media, such as plastics, or new systems such as visual music notation and the parameters of concrete poetry, inevitably alter the shape of art, the characteristics of music. and the content of poetry. New possibilities extend the range of expression of those creative people whom we identify as painters. film makers, composers, and poets. It is very rare, however, that new media and new systems should bring in their wake new people to become involved in creative activity, be it composing music, drawing, constructing or writing.</p>

<p>This has happened with the advent of computers. The engineers for whom the graphic plotter driven by a computer represented nothing more than a means of solving certain problems visually, have occasionally become so interested in the possibilities of this visual output, that they have started to make drawings which bear no practical application, and for which the only real motives are the desire to explore, and the sheer pleasure of seeing a drawing materialize. Thus people who would never have put pencil to paper, or brush to canvas, have started making images, both still and animated, which approximate and often look identical to what we call ‘art’ and put in public galleries.</p>

<p>This is the most important single revelation of this exhibition.</p>

<p>Work on this project started in the autumn of 1965. Only by 1968, however, was there enough financial support for it to go ahead. Since the project involves computers, cybernetics, electronics, music, art, poetry, machines, as well as the problem of how to present this hybrid mixture, I could not have done it on my own.</p>

<p>I was very lucky to have had the help and advice of:
technological adviser - Mark Dowson, freelance electronics and system design consultant, associated with Dr. Gordon Pask and System Research Ltd.
music adviser - Peter Schmidt, painter, who has a particular interest in electronic and computer music and who has composed music himself.
exhibition designer - Franciszka Themerson, FSIA, OGG College de Pataphysique (Paris), painter and theatrical designer.</p>

<p>Jasia Reichardt</p>


</div>
</div>
	
	<div class="collapsible-text-container">
<button class="collapsible-text-button">Notes on Cybernetics (Mark Dowson)</button>
<div class="collapsible-text-content">


<p>Robots and computers have been with us for a long time. The first computers were the abacus used thousands of years ago; the first robot (in myth, if not reality) the Golem, a man made of clay by the High Rabbi Lev Ben Bezalel of Prague in the sixteenth century. This is also the first cautionary tale about robots; for the Golem. animated by a slip of paper bearing the name of God. stuck to its forehead. turned on the Rabbi and kil led him when he made it work on the Sabbath. The word ‘robot’ comes to us from the Czech writer Karel Capek and his play, R.U.R. (Russums Universal Robots) of 1928. Meanwhile computers had been developing steadily; the first adding machine was Pascal’s calculator, 1642, followed closely by Leibniz’s calculating machine which could multiply, divide and extract roots. Automation started with Jacquard’s punch-card-controlled loom (1801) and, of course, fair ground organs controlled on a similar principle.</p>

<p>The first computer in the modern sense of a machine whose operations are controlled by its input, would have been Charles Babbage’s Analytical Engine (c .1840) had he completed it, but we must wait till this century and Bush’s Differential Analyser (1927) for the first working example of this type of machine. The Second  World War gave a spur to the development of servomechanisms and electronic computation and saw the creation of the first stored-programme digital electronic computer, ENIAC.</p>

<p>Cybernetics was born officially in 1948 with the publication of Wiener’s book - ‘Cybernetics,’ or ‘Control and communication in the animal and the machine.’ A year later, Shannon’s paper, ‘A mathematical theory of communication,’ consolidated the foundations of cybernetics as we know it today.</p>

<p>A list of a few significant events and their dates:
1642 Pascal’s calculator was built
1673 Leibniz builds his calculating machine
1801 Jacquard’s punch-card-controlled loom
1840 Babbage working on his Analytical Engine
1868 Maxwell publishes his theoretical analysis of Watt’s governor
1927 Bush constructs his Differential Analyser
1944 ENIAC constructed 
1946 First Josiah Macy Foundation conference on Cybernetics
1948 Norbert Wiener’s book Cybernetics published
1949 Shannon publishes his paper ‘The mathematical theory of communication’
1956 First congress of the International Association of Cybernetics at Namur, Belgium.</p>

<p>Since the early 1950’s the pace of work on cybernetics has been so intense and the rate of new discoveries so fast that time alone will tell which events will prove to have been crucial in the development of this still relatively young science.</p>

<p>Mark Dowson</p>


</div>
</div>
	
	<div class="collapsible-text-container">
<button class="collapsible-text-button">Computer Art (Jasia Reichardt)</button>
<div class="collapsible-text-content">


<p>‘Absolute power will corrupt not only men but machines’. In his article ‘Inventing the future’, Dennis Gabor put forward some of his expectations and fears about the function of the machine in society of the future. The above comment was made with reference to electronic predictors, which, having built up a reputation for accuracy, become aware of their infallibility (since they are learning machines) and begin to use their newly-discovered power.</p>

<p>So far electronic predictors have not become a reality. However, another postulation made by Professor Gabor in the same article (Encounter May 1960) appears to be very relevant indeed. Will the machine—he wondered-cut out the creative artist? ‘I sincerely hope’, Gabor continued, ‘that machines will never replace the creative artist, but in good conscience I cannot say that they never could.’</p>

<p>The computer performs various functions which in the broader sense seem to be the act of intelligence, i.e. manipulation of symbols, processing of information, obeying complex rules and even learning by experience. Nevertheless, the computer is not capable of making abstractions, and is devoid of the three prime forces behind creativity-imagination, intuition and emotion. Despite this, the computer as a budding artist has been making an appearance since about 1960. In 1963, the magazine Computers and Automation announced a computer art contest which has been held annually ever since. The winning design usually appears on the cover of the August issue and the runners-up are given a coverage inside. The designs vary considerably although they share certain characteristics, i.e. they are only in black and white, there is an emphasis on geometrical shapes, and they are basically linear. As designs, the computer products look bare and minimal and represent little else than the initial stage in what may be a far more challenging adventure in merging rather than relating creative activity with technology.</p>

<p>Computer graphics range from static compositions to frames of motion pictures, and could be divided into two main categories; 1. those which approximate to pure design or art; and 2. those which are not made with any aesthetic end in view but which serve to visualise complex physical phenomena.</p>

<p>At a conference dealing with computers and design in 1966 at the University of Waterloo, two statements were made which might at first have appeared unnecessarily boastful and heroic: 1. ‘The computer simply elevates the level of possible creative work’. 2. ‘The computer can handle some elements of creativity now-by current definitions of creativity’. Both these statements were made by scientists, although there exists a considerable scepticism amongst scientists as well as artists about the validity of the various experiments in this area. Others claim that the computer provides the first real possibility of a collaboration between the artist and the scientist which can only be based on each other’s familiarity with both media.</p>

<p>The first commercial computer was marketed in 1950. Ten years later the Boeing airplane company coined the term ‘computer graphics’. They used graphics for purely utilitarian purposes. These were employed, for instance, to verify the landing accuracy of a plane viewed from the pilot’s seat and the runway. They were used to establish the interaction of range of movements of the pilot in his environment of the cockpit. To this end they created a 50 percentile pilot and studied him in animation. All the drawings and the animation were done with a computer. Other experiments included visualising acoustic graphs in perspective and the production of very accurate isometric views of aeroplanes.</p>

<p>There are two main methods at present by which computer graphics are made. In the first place there are the ink drawings produced by a computer-driven plotter. The plotter, a moving pen, conveys the image direct to paper. Drawings can also be made with the images composed of different letters or figures and printed out on a typewriter which is automatically operated by the computer. In the second category are the computer graphics made on the cathode ray tube with an electron beam electrically deflected across the phosphorescent screen to produce the desired picture. A camera photographs the image in various stages and an electronic console is used to control the picture and to advance the film. Static graphics can be obtained by making enlarged photographs from the film. Whether the pictures are made for analytical purposes or just for fun, the computer graphic is a visual analogue to a sequence of calculations fed into the computer.</p>

<p>The now ‘antique’ Sketchpad which has been used for numerous experiments of this type at Massachusetts Institute of Technology since 1962, was one of the first to produce drawings on a cathode ray tube demonstrating the sort of possibilities which are inherent in the system. One could draw with a light pen on the screen simple patterns consisting of lines and curves. The operator could impose certain constrictions on the patterns he was making by demanding, for instance, by pushing the appropriate button, that the lines be made parallel, vertical or straight. At that stage the operator could not demand something as complex as a solution to the following problems: ‘These lines represent a piece of structure of a certain thickness and size and with certain cross-section characteristics, made of a particular material and obeying specific physical laws-depict this under a stress of so many pounds per cubic foot’.</p>

<p>Today the process whereby a design is adjusted at any stage of its development is already quite familiar. If the operator alters the design on the cathode ray tube with a light pen, the computer converts the altered design into electronic impulses using them to modify the pre-existing programme held in the computer’s memory store. The altered design then appears on another cathode ray tube. This system is widely used by General Motors for car body design. The image on the cathode ray tube can be shifted, rotated, enlarged, seen in perspective, stored, recalled and transferred to paper with the intermediate stages recorded on film. Since the process suggests inhibiting difficulties to someone who is not an electronic engineer, it may be difficult for an artist to imagine how he could possibly make use of a computer. The solution to the problem lies in collaboration. There are three stages in the process of producing computer graphics, or for that matter using the computer in most cases. In the first place the communicator presents his ideas or message which is to be communicated to the computer. Secondly, the communication specialist decides, unless there are specific instructions, whether the problem should be solved graphically, verbally or as a combination of both. Thirdly, the computer specialist selects the appropriate computer equipment and interprets the problem into machine language, so that the computer can act upon it. The Korean artist Nam June Paik has gone so far as to claim that in the same way that collage technique replaced oil paint, so the cathode ray tube will replace canvas. However, so far only three artists that I know of have actually produced computer graphics, the rest to date having been made by scientists.</p>

<p>At the moment the range of visual possibilities may not seem very extensive, since the computer is best used for rather more schematic and geometric forms, and those patterns and designs which are logically simple although they may look very intricate. One can programme the computer to produce patterns based on the golden section or any other specific premise, defining a set of parameters and leaving the various possibilities within them to chance. In this way certain limitations are provided within which the computer can ‘improvise’ and in the space of 20 minutes race through the entire visual potential inherent in the particular scheme. Programmed to draw variations with straight lines it is conceivable, though perhaps unlikely, that one of the graphics produced may consist simply of one line placed exactly on top of another. If there is no formula for predicting each number or step in a given sequence, the system by which this type of computer graphic comes about can be considered random.</p>

<p>Interesting results can be obtained by introducing different random elements into the programme. One can, for instance, produce a series of points on a surface which can be connected in any way with straight lines, or one can instruct the computer to draw solid geometric shapes without specifying in what sequence they are to be superimposed, leaving the overlapping of the shapes to chance.</p>

<p>A fascinating experiment was made by Michael Noll of the Bell Telephone Laboratories whereby he analysed a 1917 black-and-white, plus-and-minus picture by Mondrian and produced a number of random computer graphics using the same number of horizontal and vertical bars placed within an identical overall area. He reported that 59% of the people who were shown both the Mondrian and one of the computer versions preferred the latter, 28% identified the computer picture correctly, and 72% thought that the Mondrian was done by computer. The experiment is not involved either with proof or theory, it simply provides food for thought. Noll, who has produced a considerable number of computer graphics and animated films in America, sees them as a very initial stage in the possible relationship between the artist and computer. He does not consider himself as an artist by virtue of his graphic output. He sees himself as someone who is doing preliminary explorations in order to acquaint artists with these new possibilities.</p>

<p>Perhaps even less credible than the idea of computer-generated pictures is the idea of computer sculpture. That too has been achieved. A programme for a three-dimensional sculpture can be fed into a computer- the three-dimensional projection of a two-dimensional design. It can be transferred via punched paper tape to a milling machine which is capable of producing the physical object in three dimensions.</p>

<p>The computer is only a tool which, at the moment, still seems far removed from those polemic preoccupations which concern art. However, even now seen with all the prejudices of tradition and time, one cannot deny that the computer demonstrates a radical extension in art media and techniques. The possibilities inherent in the computer as a creative tool will do little to change those idioms of art which rely primarily on the dialogue between the artist, his ideas, and the canvas. They will, however, increase the scope of art and contribute to its diversity.</p>

<p>Jasia Reichardt</p>


</div>
</div>
	
	<script>
var coll = document.getElementsByClassName("collapsible-text-button");
var i;

for (i = 0; i < coll.length; i++) {
  coll[i].addEventListener("click", function() {
    this.classList.toggle("active");
    var container = this.parentElement;
    var content = this.nextElementSibling;
    if (content.style.maxHeight){
      content.style.maxHeight = null;
      container.classList.remove("expanded");
    } else {
      container.classList.add("expanded");
      content.style.maxHeight = content.scrollHeight + "px";
    } 
  });
}
</script>

	
	<h3>Explore the Catalogue</h3>
	
	<iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/cybernetic-serendipity" width="100%" height="500" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen></iframe>
	
	<p><em>This is a preview only - <a href="https://archive.org/details/cybernetic-serendipity" target="_blank">view fullsize on archive.org</a></em></p>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Vinyl LP</h2>
	
	

<table id="infobox">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2">
                <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/lp_cover.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/lp_cover.jpg"></a>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2" id="infobox-subtitle"><cite>Cybernetic Serendipity Music</cite></td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publisher</th>
            <td>Institute of Contemporary Arts, London</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publishing date</th>
            <td>1968</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Format</th>
            <td>Vinyl</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Duration</th>
            <td>52:44</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        
    </tbody>
</table>

	
	<p>A vinyl record was available for purchase which included audio excerpts from cybernetic music.</p>
	
	<div class="quote">
	<p>During the preparation of the Cybernetic Serendipity exhibition two things became apparent. 

	<p>One, that in order to show what was going on in the field computer music, it was necessary to include a considerable amount of material that was not strictly composed with or played by computer. Two, that dealing with an exploratory field, all attempts at a historical perspective or firm evaluation were out of place. The exhibition and this record, therefore, are essentially a reportage of current trends and developments in programmed and stochastic music.</p>
	
	<p>The first landmark in computer composition is Lejaren A. Hiller’s <em>Illiac Suite</em>, 1957. Many experiments have been carried out before, but these were either exploratory without yielding a tangible music, or were mostly concerned with the technical possibilities of imitating familiar sounds.</p>

	<p>Ideas which are relevant to composition with computers were frequently employed in the experimental musical composition of the past thirty years. The work of Joseph Schillinger, for instance, through its systematic analysis and programming, antedates the methods employed by computer composers today. The notion of randomness exemplified in the work of John Cage is also of crucial importance. Randomness (decision avoiding, or more concisely, leaving a decision to chance within an exactly specified range of possibilities) is one of the most important tools of the computer composer.</p>

	<p>Computer music falls into two categories: computer composition and computer sound. Specific works may employ one or both of these. <em>Illiac Suite</em> is computer composed but performed by a string quartet. Pieces by James Tenney, Gerald Strang and Peter Zinovieff utilise the computer both as a tool to compose with and a sound-making instrument. The experimental pieces produced at Bell Telephone Laboratories make use of existing tunes like <em>A bicycle built for two</em> but played and sung by a computer.</p>

	<p>As a souvenir of the Cybernetic Serendipity exhibition this record is a selection of work in progress.</p> 

	The cover shows a section of a score for <em>Four Sacred April Rounds</em> 1968 by Peter Zinovieff.</p>
	
	<p class="quote-attrib">- Liner notes</p>
	</div>
	
	<h3>Audio</h3>
	
	<iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/cybernetic-serendipity-music&playlist=1&list_height=150" width="100%" height="100" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen></iframe>
	
	<p><em><a href="https://archive.org/details/cybernetic-serendipity-music" target="_blank">Download the audio from archive.org</a></em></p>
	
	<p><strong>Tracklisting:</strong></p>
	<ul>
		<li>A1. Lejaren Hiller &amp; Leonard Isaacson - Illiac Suite (Experiment 4) (4:00)</li>
		<li>A2. John Cage - Cartridge Music (Excerpt) (4:00)</li>
		<li>A3. Iannis Xenakis - Strategie (Excerpt) (5:00)</li>
		<li>A4. Wilhelm Fucks - Experiment Quatro-Due (5:00)</li>
		<li>A5. J. K. Randall - Mudgett (Excerpt) (7:30)</li>
		<li>B1. Gerald Strang - Composition 3 (2:30)</li>
		<li>B2. Haruki Tsuchiya - Bit Music (Excerpt) (2:30)</li>
		<li>B3. T. H. O'Beirne - Enneadic Selections (4:30)</li>
		<li>B4. Peter Zinovieff - January Tensions (10:30)</li>
		<li>B5. Herbert Brün - Infraudibles (8:30)</li>
	</ul>
	
	Dates of composition:
	<ul>
		<li>A1 - 1957</li>
		<li>A2 - 1960</li>
		<li>A3 - 1962</li>
		<li>A4 - 1963</li>
		<li>A5 - 1965</li>
		<li>B1 - 1966</li>
		<li>B2 - 1968</li>
		<li>B3 - 1968</li>
		<li>B4 - 1968</li>
		<li>B5 - 1967</li>
	</ul>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Gallery</h2>
	
	<section
		data-featherlight-gallery
		data-featherlight-filter="a"
		class="gallery-grid"
		>
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/cybernetic_044.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/cybernetic_044.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Nicolas Schöffer - <em>Cybernetic Light Tower</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/cybernetic_054.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/cybernetic_054.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Margaret Masterman &amp; Robin McKinnon Wood - <em>Computerized Japanese Haiku</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
		
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/cybernetic_091.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/cybernetic-serendipity/cybernetic_091.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Calcomp Plotting System</figcaption>
			</figure>
	</section>
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="cybernetics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[is the title of a special 1968 issue of the British magazine 'Studio International.' The issue was first published to coincide with an exhibition entitled 'Cybernetic Serendipity,' dealing broadly with the demonstration of how humans can use the computer and new technology to extend creativity and inventiveness.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Klankteksten - Konkrete Poëzie - Visuele Teksten</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/article/klankteksten/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Klankteksten - Konkrete Poëzie - Visuele Teksten" /><published>2021-03-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-03-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/article/klankteksten</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/article/klankteksten/"><![CDATA[<section>
	

<table id="infobox">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2">
                <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/klankteksten/front.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/klankteksten/front.jpg"></a>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2" id="infobox-subtitle"><cite>Sound Texts - Concrete Poetry - Visual Texts</cite></td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publisher</th>
            <td>Stedelijk Museum, Amsterdam</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publishing date</th>
            <td>November 1970</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
    </tbody>
</table>


	<p><strong>Klankteksten - Konkrete Poëzie - Visuele Teksten</strong> (Sound Texts - Concrete Poetry - Visual Texts) is the title of an exhibition catalogue released in conjunction with the exhibition 'Klankteksten?' at the Stedelijk Museum in Amsterdam, Netherlands in November 1970. The exhibition provided an overview of the concrete poetry movement.<p>
</section>

<section>
	<h2 class="header-nestled">Exhibition</h2>
	

<div class="thumbnail-container">
    <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/klankteksten/1970-1971_amsterdam_overzichtstentoonstelling-konkrete-poezie.jpg"><img class="thumbnail-image" src="/assets/articles/klankteksten/1970-1971_amsterdam_overzichtstentoonstelling-konkrete-poezie.jpg"></a>
    
    <div class="thumbnail-caption">Installation view including <em>Revolution</em> (1969).</div>
    
</div>

	
	<div class="quote">
	<p>The exhibition came at a time when concrete poetry was in a crisis position internationally. This crisis situation was reflected in the question mark that appears in the title of the exhibition. After all, concrete poetry was declared dead in the English magazine Stereo-headphones.</p>
	
	<p>The exhibition was divided into different sections: a didactic one in which some forms and methods in visual poetry were presented; and the representation of the diversity of constellations and arrangements (mainly typographical) divided into different groupings or geographic regions. As a result, the exhibition was in danger of becoming historic. De Vree was the great advocate for reversing this with the establishment of a third section entitled Open End. This more forward-looking section accommodated poetic work by artists who also used other visual means than purely typographical, often incorporating clear expressions of political-social or conceptual thoughts. Most of these poets will later group themselves into <em>Lotta Poetica</em>, the international artists' magazine founded by Sarenco and Paul De Vree in 1971.</p>
	
	<p class="quote-attrib">- <a href="http://ensembles.mhka.be/events/klankteksten-konkrete-poezie-visuele-teksten" target="_blank">M HKA Ensembles, ? Klankteksten, konkrete poëzie, visuele teksten</a></p>
	</div>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Exhibition Catalogue</h2>
	
	<p>The exhibition catalogue is approximately 230 pages long, and contains texts on concrete poetry from the exhibition curators in Dutch, English, and French. The catalogue is divided into sections, including <em>Some forms and working methods in visual poetry</em>, writer biographies, a bibliography of concrete poetry publications, and listings of exhibitions and recordings. Many of the concrete poems have been reproduced in full-page format.</p>
	
	<h3>Essays</h3>
	
	<div class="collapsible-text-container">
<button class="collapsible-text-button">Introduction (Liesbeth Crommelin)</button>
<div class="collapsible-text-content">


<p>The exhibition ‘Concrete Poetry ?’ features over one hundred artists. The complexity of the setup required an exceptionally great organisational endeavour, for which homage is due to miss Liesbeth Crommelin, deputy-curator of the Museum’s department of Applied Art. Apart from her study of the matter in hand and her untiring efforts, along with the devoted care of the secretariat which could hardly cope with the spate of poetic contributions, we were committed to advice and actual assistance from outside, which, in fact, has been extended to us in a generous and profuse manner. In various countries, our advisors have collected material for the benefit of the exhibition. We owe a great debt of gratitude to the following persons:</p>

<p>Pierre Garnier, France
Haroldo deCampos, South-America
Reinhard Döhl, Germany
Bob Cobbing, England
Paul de Vree, Belgium and the Netherlands
Seiichi Niikuni, Japan
Bohumila Grögerova and Josef Hirsal, Czechoslovakia
Emmett Williams, USA
Hansjörg Mayer, Germany and England
Ugo Carrega and Sarenco, Italy
Michael Rhodes, Canada</p>

<p>In addition, as the preparatory operations proceeded, all kinds of new work were sent in; it was all viewed and graded during two strenuous weekends. During the stimulating discussions with Paul de Vree, Hansjörg Mayer, Bob Cobbing and Reinhard Döhl, the setup as well as the title of the exhibition were constantly subject to change and under fire of criticism. Bob Cobbing handled the material for the longplay record as well as the program for the tape recorders; Hansjörg Mayer consulted with general public.</p>

<p>In the Netherlands for one, which on the score of its limited language territory, finds itself from the start at a disadvantage, it has been possible since 1962 to get acquainted with the latest ideas on visual poetry, notably through the extremely well documented publications in the periodical De Tafelronde, published at Antwerp by Paul de Vree. There are in the Dutch language area in all some six magazines that are almost entirely committed to this visual aspect of poetry. In the official literary press in Holland, however, visual poetry is all but totally ignored; not until this year (1970), on the spur of the publication of some visual poetry in book form, did the literary columns of a few dailies and weeklies devote some more column space to this event. Could it be that we Dutchmen are by nature wary of amalgamating individual disciplines ? On surveying the international publications in this field, we are bound to recognize that we are here indeed concerned with a professional field, alas with the inevitable concommittant issues of birthright, confusion of ideas, etc. We have tried to be as objective as possible in our approach of the matter in hand, but realize full well that we have not been successful all the way. While, on the one hand, it was obvious that a movement which originated some twenty years ago, has by now become a closed historical chapter, on the other hand it seemed equally conceivable that its influence or aftereffect might evolve along entirely different lines according to tradition, personality or circumstances.
In the spring of 1970, Nicolas Zurbrugg collected, in the magazine Stereo Headphones, a number of stagements on the death of concrete poetry, as voiced by various well-known poets in this field. The opinions ranged from fierce attacks on those artists who continue to work on the old established lines and don’t, in fact, achieve more than feeble typographical jokes, to the recognition of the ‘death’ of concrete poetry which would clear the road for the emergence of new forms in poetry.</p>

<p>What we have tried to visualize in the present exhibition, is</p>

<p>a.
the evolution of the new typovisual forms as from 1950;
b.
poetry which avails itself also of other plastic means than the printed (or typewritten) character.</p>

<p>The first section of the exhibition opens with the somewhat isolated figure of Carlo Belloli, disciple of Marinetti’s, who constitutes in a way a transition from the futurist ideas to the ‘concrete’ thinking of around 1950. The second section shows the afore mentioned major influential groups and individuals who worked quite independently in various places. Next is shown, in a rather random order, work originated in a number of countries, in particular publications by people who have been creative in this field since before 1965. An exception has been made for Japan which country, on account of its fundamentally heterogeneous characters, was difficult to place in a chronological pattern, and also for Czechoslovakia which, as a result of its isolation, has produced work of such an individual character that it baffles all efforts to distinguish different periods.</p>

<p>The last section of the exhibition features artists who search for other than purely typographic means to make poetry ‘concrete’. They include authors who either originally came under the first group but have changed their working methods afterwards or, from the start, used other formative means and who, in many instances, appear to think in terms of politico-social or philosophical ideas as is evidenced by a number of texts by Italian and French poets which share many properties with other forms of plastic art. A third group is formed by some of the latest examples of typovisual expression having an originality of their own and of their own time.</p>

<p>To the end of elucidating the didactic side of the exhibition, it was thought appropriate to open with a number of examples of working methods that visitors may identify in the exhibited texts. The grouping as shown in this opening section, has been derived, in a shorter version, from the exhibition Text Buchstabe Bild which was organized in Zürich this summer by Felix Baumann and Reinhard Döhl.</p>

<p>I have refrained from giving here a definition of what concrete poetry is, on the assumption that the essays by Bob Cobbing, Reinhard Döhl and Paul de Vree included in the catalogue, present an illuminating description of, respectively, its phonetic, its linguistic and its graphic-visual aspects.</p>

<p>Liesbeth Crommelin</p>


</div>
</div>
	
	<div class="collapsible-text-container">
<button class="collapsible-text-button">Visual Poetry (Paul de Vree)</button>
<div class="collapsible-text-content">


<p>In order to obviate all misunderstanding as to visual poetry (i.e. the form) which, in its concrete manifestation, obviously tends toward graphic and plastic art, we’ll have to elucidate the difference with the current trend in plastic art to use lettering and printed texts (cf Cubism and Merz), i.e. semantics(1) as constituent material for a composition and/or structure. In both cases, we are concerned with the phenomenon of ‘Vermischungen’ (amalgamations, fusions) which Helmut Heissenbüttel views as characteristic of the development of art in the 20th century, and which has spawned as yet unnamed forms of art. In the former instance, however, the poets still adhere to the notion of poetry, because through the text - however rudimentary, reduced or truncated - they are confronted with an optical process. The text remains primary. It appears often difficult to clearly differentiate in these matters. For not infrequently, visual poetry is practised by poets who are also painters or inversely. A great number of these works may therefore be labeled as standing ‘between poetry and painting’.</p>

<p>In general terms, the definition as formulated by the Bolivian Swiss Eugen Gomringer and the Brasilian Noigandres group is central to the visual aspect of concrete poetry: the conscious perception of the material and its structure, the material as the sum total of all the signs with which we make poetry. This vision of poetry did not come out of the blue around 1955. Since Stéphan Mallarmé (Un coup de dés jamais n’abolira le hasard), it developed via futurism (F. T. Marinetti), Dadaism (H. Ball, R. Hausmann, Tristan Tzara), Sic (P. Albert-Birot) and De Stijl (Theo van Doesburg) to the proto-concrete conception of Carlo Belloli (1944-1951) and poetic lettrism (1945, I. Isou, R. Altmann) and finally came to full fruition in Gomringer’s ‘Konstellationen’ who, inspired by Max Bill, pointedly transformed semantics1 into a graphic pattern. This optical process derives from the vision that wants to reestablish the organic function of poetry in society and, consequently, to make poetry directly visible as an object meant to be seen and used. What is primarily envisaged here is a rediscovery of constituent elements (Gomringer), a breaking-down of linguistic elements to the end of achieving new material (Fahlström). (Here the difference with Dada is apparent this movement obviously was aimed at the parodic negation and destruction of bourgeois culture and only later, at first intuitively, then consciously, engaged itself in formative issues.) The constellation hinges on the juxtaposition (repetatively or combinationwise) of a group of words whose intermetric relations, in order to be seen, demand a typographic enhancement (M. Weaver). ‘Aesthetically’, Max Bense adds, the scope or play of a sentence (a text) is the sentence itself, i.e. identical with (…) its material realization.’ (‘Essentially, play is a realization, not a code’). This accounts for the research carried out by the ‘Materialgruppe’ of Darmstadt. Emmett Williams, Diter Rot, Claus Bremer and André Tomkins organize concretizations that consist predominantly of the regular typewriter print and derive their significance from the systematic handling of the text. In this perspective, the importance of the alphabet which had already been used before as a poetic ingredient by such typographers as Hendrik Nikolaas Werkman and by the lettrists, becomes evident.</p>

<p>With reference to Franz Mon’s ‘Artikulationen’, Carlfriedrich Claus, (in Nota 4, 1960, p. 42-43) remarked how the characters as such, through their proportions, their power of attraction and repulsion, their flowing and intersecting (horizontal-static or vertical and diagonaldynamic) impart, as it were, word meaning to each individual letter and, optically as well as acoustically, create a new universe. This was taken up by Dorn Silvester Houédard in his cosmically charged typestracts, but it is especially Pierre and Ilse Garnier who have built their spatialism on this principle. Primarily, however, spatialism is aimed at making the body partake in the realization of a poem - in this respect, it is allied to the ars poëtica of the audiopoet or sound poetry poet Henri Chopin it sees language as a living organism endowed with energy. This energy is unleashed to advantage in the mechanical poetry 1 (impulsively) and in the visual (script) language planes of Carl-friedrich Claus and others, an arresting, labyrinthical example of ‘the visual encompassing the readable’. The mechanical poem 1 is a micro-structure which, on the spur of psycho-physical impulses (tied in with the engagement of body, hands, fingers, eyes plus the machine), creates a visual unit in which syntax is atomised, chance incorporated, areas of language and tension are projected. The result springs from a gesture. (In painting, the mechanical poem has its counterpart in action painting and kinetism.) In the mechanical poetry 2 the topography (spatial disposition) of the linguistic material is more homogenous and more modular. While the typewriter still reflects the lyrical impulse - witness the French-Japanese nature poems by Pierre Garnier and Seichi Niikuni, the whirling explositives of De Vree’s and Bengt Emil Johnson’s visionary clusters of characters -, with the typography as practiced, in an autonomous (i.e. aesthetic) way, by the Stuttgart group, a more radical, rational, structural and definitely more typovisual trend has set in. In Hansjörg Mayer’s ‘Typoems’, ‘Alfabetenquadratbilder’ and ‘Typaktionen’, the functional small futura letter is rampant, while the ‘Poem structures in the Looking Glass’ by Klaus Burkhardt and Reinhard Döhl are built up, purely topographically (in line with photo and film techniques) with letters, numbers and words. The above mentioned visual manifestations -mostly found in countries like Czechoslovakia, Italy (Modulo group), France (spatialism), Germany, Austria and Brasil - are covered by the formula which Siegfried J. Schmidt - on the line of Van Doesburg’s postulate - gives of concretevisual poetry: it is a non-mimetc, generative art that does away with the sensorial perception of visual reality and concentrates on the thematic development of its devices (linguistic units and textual structures). He takes exception, though, to acrobatic typography which threatens to burst through the boundaries of graphic art and which also Gomringer signals as a potential danger.</p>

<p>This view does not quite tally, however, with the one that sees the historic roots of visual poetry in the earlier figure poems, emblems, calligrams, ideograms and such like. From the start, the Noigandres group has referred to the work of Apollinaire, Marinetti and the Dadaists, what is more, to the use of extra-linguistic elements, viz. semiotics.(2) The English concrete poets, including Scottish Ian Hamilton Finlay, John Furnival, Edwin Morgan and others, followed, if not always with the same objective, by the Americans M. E. Solt, R. P. Brown, M. J. Phillips, J. Hollander), the Belgians (Paul de Vree), the Dutchmen (F. van der Linde, H. Clavin, H. Deman), the Germans (R. Döhl, C. Bremer, F. Kriwet), the Frenchmen (H. Chopin, J. Blaine, J.-F. Bory), the Japanese (Kitasono Katue) and others, realized poems-in-the-shape-of or, in other words, mimetic, optical-semantic tautologies, ‘imaged words’ (a neologism coined by Kostelanetz) that not infrequently serve as outlets for humor, grotesque and criticism (witness Furnival’s architectural mammoth Towers of Babel).</p>

<p>The influence of popart and new realism (i.e. references to scenery, personalities, cities, objects) can be traced in present-day poetrygraphy, while also photography and letter drawings break up the geometric-typographic models (the French Approches group). The Amodulo group (Sarenco) rebels against the f utura letter in that it uses baroque headlines. Whereas the simbiotics(3) of Ugo Carrega advocates the merger of verbal, verbo-graphic and graphic elements (sign, form and color), semiotics 2 adheres to non-verbal elements that are explained by key-signs (D. Pigni-tari, L. A. Pinto). The Foundpoems and Newspoems as introduced by E. Morgan, consisting of short-lived topical materials (clippings from dailies and weeklies), are increasingly practised (among others by M. Perfetti and L. Ori).</p>

<p>In the three-dimensional range, mention should be made of the object poems, e.g. the Music-box and the Theatre-project by Alain Arias Misson together with the printed character compositions of P. A. Gette. A great number of concrete poets, including Ian Hamilton Finlay, Ugo Carrega, Sarenco, are currently engaged in work executed in plastic constructions.</p>

<p>End notes:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>The term semantic, derived from the Greek adjective semantikos (= meaning, that which means, signifies, informs), came into usage around 1887. It denotes the relationship between a linguistic form and the concomitant mental process of symbolism involved in the act of speech. In broader outline, semantics is the doctrine of the meaning of words, a side -discipline of linguistics, a science involved in the study of language and languages in all their aspects (structure, history, mutual relations, interrelations with all other modes of human behavior). Translating semantics into graphic art relates to the manner in which linguistic signs, as to shape and spatiality, no longer evolve as textual lines but as textual planes. In terms of concrete realization, they don’t appear as a message but as visual aesthetic information.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Semiotics is the domain of Max Bense and Elisabeth Walther. In his Theorie der Texte, Bense departs from aesthetic information which objectively establishes the aesthetic status of an object, i.e. a text in its material elements and describes it independent of the subject (the author) and the observer (the interpretant). The aesthetic information does not transmit a meaning, only its own realization. The process of realization precedes the process of information. Language can only be extant through language. AH the rest makes language to an illusion. What is at stake is an awareness of linguistic possibilities. One aspect of the text problem is the semiotic analysis which applies semiotics, i.e. the doctrine of signs. A sign is understood to be anything which stands for something else to arouse the same gamut of reactions. A sign is everything that is presented as a sign and only that. A sign is a triadic relation between an object (which is signaled), a means (which, as a sign, takes the place of an object) and an interpretant (on whom, through the means as a sign, the object is focused). This triadic relation should not be neglected when evaluating visual opetry. (For further information, I should like to refer to Bense’s ‘Semiotik’).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The scrittura simbiotica distinguishes six categories of signs or elements in analysing the signs on a printed page. In terms of words, it distinguishes the propositional (semantic) and the phonetic (sound) elements. The printed character of which the physical structure is emphasized, acts as a verbographic agent. Purely graphic elements are the sign in a semiotic sense, Reform (geometric structures, etc.) and the color as a semantic, non-plastic constituent. AH these elements make for a symbiosis of organic structures that affect each other to advantage. Thus arises, not a logical, but a ubicentric poetry, a multiple textual space that implies the gesture as its context. This reveals another tangent with spatialism. In the last analysis, I cannot alert the interpretant enough to the fact that, alongside imagination (ingeniousness), action is a primary agent in the realization of concrete poetry (both acoustically and visually).</p>
  </li>
</ol>


</div>
</div>
	
	<div class="collapsible-text-container">
<button class="collapsible-text-button">Some Remarks on Concrete Poetry (Reinhard Döhl)</button>
<div class="collapsible-text-content">


<p>in the overall picture, the manifesto’s of the fifties, the tentative anthologies, exhibitions and essays of the sixties, in their efforts to delineate, to collect and to describe what concrete literature, resp. concrete poetry actually is, present a plenty of not only terminological differences and blurred notions, well before and concurrent with the rather belatedly accredited term ‘concrete literature’, we meet with such expressions (often used either synonymously or but slightly varying in meaning) as ‘elementary’, ‘abstract’, ‘absolute’, ‘material literature’ with mostly striking parallels in a so-called literary revolution, time and again, the terms concrete and visual poetry are used as synonyms, whereas visual and phonetic poetry are clearly differentiated, and while heissenbüttel views the concept concrete poetry as coined on the pattern of concrete art, fahlström, in his manifesto, employs the term concrete rather ‘as relative to concrete music than to concretism of imagery’.</p>

<p>in the face of this dilemma, schmidthenner resignedly admits that the authors of concrete poetry only concur in that they insist that ‘what is materially concrete in language should be incorporated in the production of literature’ but otherwise agree to differ widely as to ‘what should, still or already, be considered as coming in the pale of concrete poetry’. i believe, however, that, in a broader perspective, farther reaching aspects may be gained, when we are prepared to conceive of literature as a process of which concrete literature is in fact but a phase; and that, by attempting to understand concrete literature from its historic roots, we may find access to it in a meaningful way.</p>

<p>the manifesto’s of the fifties dealing with concrete literature concur in stressing that the literary product is a primarily linguistic happening; they aim at excluding all that is subjectively incidental, oppose traditional habits of writing and reading, call for new modes of writing and reading, and view, with max bill, the literary product as an object for intellectual use. in his vision, bill refers, by and large, to an art that in its self-awareness - in order to answer the definition ‘concrete’ - should be dated not later than 1930, i.e. following the publication of the first and only issue of van doesburg’s magazine ‘art concret’. like various other manifesto’s of the mid-and late twenties, the ‘manifesto of concrete art’ as published in this issue, does not formulate a new beginning but presents a systematic review of the various individual achievements of the artistic revolution, whether the notion ‘concrete’, relating to plastic art, was used before 1930, cannot be conclusively substantiated; is, however, highly probable.</p>

<p>in the present state of research, it is deemed unlikely that the term ‘concrete poetry’ was already current usage at such an early date, yet a retrospective essay by arp, ‘kandinsky, Ie poète’ (1951), published prior to the early manifesto’s of fahlström and gomringer, includes some revealing clues: ‘in 1912 i visited with kandinsky in munich. (…) it was the time in which abstract art started its transformation into concrete art. (…) in the year of dada, poems by kandinsky were read for the first time in cabaret Voltaire in Zürich (…). the dadaists were fervent protagonists of concrete poetry, in 1916, hugo ball and tristan tzara wrote onomatopoeic poems that have substantially contributed to bringing concrete poetry into clear focus, my volume of poems ‘die wolkenpumpe’ contains mainly concrete poems, kandinsky’s body of poems ‘klänge’ is one of the outstanding great books. (…) in these poems, there are sequences of words and sentences (…) that (…) remind the reader of the continuous flux and birth of things, often with a vein of dark humor and, what is characteristic of concrete poetry, non-didactic, in one of goethe’s poems, the reader is alerted, in a poetic manner, to the fact that man must die and be reborn, kandinsky, on the other hand, confronts the reader with a dying and resuscitating word image, a dying and resuscitating word order (…).’ meaningful in this respect is that arp sets goethe’s poem against that of kandinsky, the poetically didactic poem against the linguistic manifestation, the symbolic against the concrete poem, one might stretch this statement by saying that just as goethe, in formulating his idea of the symbol, offsets the symbolic manner of speech, as truly poetic, against the allegorical parlance (of the 18th century), arp contrasts the concrete mode of expression with the symbolic parlance (of the 19th century), as a case in point: goethe’s symbolic poem ‘wanderers nachtlied’ (über allen gipfeln), resp. its dialectic inversion in brecht’s ‘lithurgie vom hauch’, is superseded in concrete literature by gomringer’s one-word constellation ‘schweigen’, resp. achtleitner’s linguistic demonstration of restlessness (‘ruh und’), the beginnings of concrete literature date indeed back to the literary confrontation with a traditionally symbolic mode of expression, this may be exemplified by works of the other exponents mentioned by arp, ball and tzara, in the field of phonetic poetry as well as by arp’s own poems, in many ways similar to kandinsky’s ‘klänge’, so much admired by arp, they bespeak the confrontation by their linguistic and verbal playing with literary ingredients, by converting sense into nonsense, eventually, they lead, beyond this toying with colloquial language, to the tryout of new linguistic devices, to the innovation of novel syntactic forms (e.g. permutation), to the initiation of a new way of speaking in the poem, e.g. in the ‘konfigurationen’, resp. ‘konstellationen’ of 1930.</p>

<p>it is not just accidental that in the line of ancestors of concrete literature, the name of apollinaire figures, his much quoted ‘il pleut’, still fully steeped in the tradition of symbolic imagery, takes a traditional lyrical image literally and externalizes it, as it were, in the typogram, other ‘calli-grammes’ of his hand evince - e.g. by the pointed introductions of colloquial props -a progressive erosion of the symbolic imagery, when, in the late fifties, the noigandres group finally calls for the suppression of all metaphoric approximations, it marks the end of a process, sparked by apollinaire and others, in which, in keeping with concrete literature, the traditional literary image was superseded by the extra-linguistic, f igurate relationship, the typographic model, the multitude of resulting possibilities reveals itself in a gamut ranging from near tautologies (when kolar organizes the letters of the name albers into albers-squares) to the intended contradiction of typographical image and text (when bremer inscribes words of the sermon on the mount in the picture of two tanks).</p>

<p>crucial to this figurate typography is the demand voiced by the italian futurists of the ‘parole in libertà’: that the text be liberated from its traditional left-to-right sequential flow, a freedom which opens up the possibility of positioning signs, syllables, sounds, words and groups of words freely over the page, the call for the disruption of traditional syntax has assigned part of the role and function of established syntax to typography; it has inaugurated in literature, as it were, a typographic syntax, accordingly, the role of italian futurism has been of major importance in the early history of concrete literature in which moreover, through the personality of marinetti’s disciple and protégé belloli, it flows out almost without transition.</p>

<p>the ‘parole in libertà’ have been criticized as being disruptive for form and content, what the critics do not sufficiently realize is that their call for freedom sprang from the confrontation with a literature that was irretrievably anchored in the category of content, the concept of form as a traditional poetic entity, the duality of form and content, style and quality, heissenbüttel - whose line of thought i largely adopt - has qualified this confrontation as a process of reduction of the content and liquidation of the form in their traditional manifestations, and has come to the conclusion that, in the thus effected reduction and back-orientation of language itself, the issue of form and content has become irrelevant, meaningless.</p>

<p>what heissenbüttel, on this score, illustrates with texts of gertrude stein, another exponent of concrete literature, i.e. reduction to the variation of a model, is further conclusive evidence of concrete texts, one might, for instance, organize the purely formal setup of an exhibition in such a way that the number of words that go into the making of the text, decreases progressively, until eventually the text consists of just one single word; this gomringer once called the ideal concrete poem, one could, indeed, trace this process of reduction back beyond the word and show it up in all possible visual constellations of syllables or even mere letters, also in this field, yet another champion of concrete literature, kurt schwitters, in his so-called ‘elementar-gedichte’, has already come up with some exemplary reduction models and, with the free typography of his ‘composed f igurate poem’, has blurred the boundaries with plastic art. when, in 1960, heissenbüttel claims: ‘reduction must engender wit’, it obviously points to the danger of sterility, the eventuality of unimaginative playing with typographic forms, yet in his program he includes the joke or pun as an essential asset of the reduced textual, verbal or character model, this, indeed, is an inherent element of the works of f inlay and jandl.</p>

<p>but schwitters, although somewhat underrated as to his merits for the development of concrete literature, appears to be a ‘witness for the crown’ for yet another, wider aspect, i.e. for the increasing difficulty of discerning whether, in dealing with the numerous specimens of concrete literature, we are, in fact, confronted with poetry to be looked at or with pictures to be read, ‘i have’, he notes in 1921, ‘pasted poems together from words and sentences in such a way that their rhythmic positioning represents a drawing, conversely, i have pasted together pictures and drawings so as to make sentences that must be read my object was to obliterate the boundaries between the various arts.’</p>

<p>a last significant ‘witness for the crown’ should be named here: stéphan mallarmé from whose ‘un coup de dés’ gomringer has derived the motto of his first manifesto. what karl einstein has formulated for mallarmé: that he was concerned with ‘the difficult point where language can only justify its existence by being pinned down in the contrast of the written black and the virginal white of the paper’ - this indeed is reflected in texts such as gomringer’s ‘das schwarze geheimnis’, in numerous works of gappmayr and others, in this context, there is clearly a certain capacity for linguistic mysticism in some of the authors of concrete literature.</p>

<p>without going into a detailed inventory, the foregoing covers, in broad outline, the precinct of concrete poetry, nevertheless, the picture, it seems to me, justifies the statement that concrete literature can only be understood from its basis, from its historic origins, its break-away from ‘the poetic structure that had existed for some hundred years’, from ‘the structural unity of modern european lyric poetry’ much criticized by friedrich, occurred in its early days, whether concrete literature, as a form of poetry ‘that does not deal with language as just an object, but wants language to speak itself’, ‘inaugurates not only a new but an ultimate phase in the formative history of poetry’, as wagenknecht suggests, this question will perhaps be answered by the present exhibition of works of the last twenty years, in addition, it should also reveal whether the criteria found in the precinct of concrete literature, indeed lead to concrete literature or point to a development through and beyond it.</p>


</div>
</div>
	
	<div class="collapsible-text-container">
<button class="collapsible-text-button">Concrete Sound Poetry 1950-1970 (Bob Cobbing)</button>
<div class="collapsible-text-content">


<p>The first use of the term ‘concrete poetry’ in a manifesto was by Öyvind Fahlström (Sweden) in 1953. He related it more to concrete music than to concrete ‘art’. He emphasised rhythm as ‘the most elementary, directly physically grasping means of effect’ because of its ‘connection with the pulsation of breathing, the blood, ejaculation.’ He opened the way not only for the structural aspects of concrete poetry which play such a prominent part in the theory and practice of Eugen Gomringer (Switzerland), the Brazilians and the Germans, but for expressionist aspects which a second generation of concrete poets has found so potent. bpIMichol (Canada) says that ‘for too many people, concrete poetry is a head trip, which is to say an intellectual trip, and as such I can look at it and admire it. For most people I know it’s a gut experience.’
Fahlström in 1953illustrated what he called a fundamental concrete principle by referring to Pierre Shaeffer’s key discovery in concrete music when he isolated a small fragment of a sound and repeated it with a change of pitch, then returned to the first pitch, and so on. This anticipated one line of development in concrete sound poetry, the electronic-musical one. Fahlström himself did not produce sound poetry until 1961.</p>

<p>The other line, the phonetic one, was anticipated much earlier by such poets as Lewis Carroll (‘twas brillig, 1855), Morgenstern (kroklokwafzi, c. 1890), Sheerbart (kikakoku ! - ekoralaps ! 1897), Khlebnikov, Hugo Ball, Pierre Albert-Birot, Marinetti, Raoul Hausmann, Kurt Schwitters (Ur sonata, 1923-28), Michel Seuphor, Camille Bryen and, within the period covered by this exhibition, Antonin Artaud and Hans Helms.
Sound poetry exists today in a diversity of forms and styles in more than a dozen different countries. Present-day developments had their real beginning in France in the early nineteen-fifties. Concrete sound poetry today is both a return to the primitive and a succession of steps into the technological era. Sten Hanson (Sweden) has described it as ‘a homecoming for poetry, a return to its source close to the spoken word, the rhythm and atmosphere of language and the body, their rites and sorcery.’ Whereas Henri Chopin (France) sees it as finding ‘its sources in the very sources of language and, by the use of electro-magnetics, as owing almost nothing to any aesthetic or historical system of poetry.’ Strangely enough, the invention of the tape-recorder has given the poet back his voice. For, by listening to their voices on the tape-recorder, with its ability to amplify, slow down and speed up voice vibrations, poets have been able to analyse and then immensely improve their vocal resources. Where the tape-recorder leads, the human voice can follow.</p>

<p>However, in 1950, Francois Dufrêne and Gils Wolman (France) began to make their cri-rhythmes and mégapneumes without any aid from the tape-recorder. They had gone back beyond the word, beyond the alphabet to direct vocal outpourings which completely unified form and content. They were back where poetry and music began. In primitive song, the melody often starts on a high note, generally falsetto, and descends. High is high both in volume and in pitch; low is both soft and deep. The emotional outburst, the physical giving out of sound and breath is the song. One thinks of primitive song on hearing FranQois Dufrêne. His cri-rhythmes employ the utmost variety of utterances, extended cries, shrieks, ululations, purrs, yarrs, yaups and duckings, the apparently uncontrollable controlled into a spontaneously shaped performance. Wolman places more emphasis on breath sounds and works in shorter, more isolated, less rhythmically organised soundunits. Both performed at first live, and later recorded their creations on tape, the tape-recorder being used simply as a recording instrument.</p>

<p>However, Dufrêne gradually warmed towards the more creative aspects of the tape-recorder and other electronic devices, which he had at first regarded as contaminations. He began to superimpose one recorded performance over another, and to use certain varieties of echo effect and reverberation. This was mainly from about 1963 onwards, although there are earlier examples. At this time, Jean-Louis Brau also employed similar echo and reverberation techniques in his instrumentations verbales.</p>

<p>While Brau and Wolman seem to have been less active recently, Dufrêne has continued with a steady output of cri-rhythmes, exhibiting the utmost virtuosity and mastery in an area of sound poetry he has made his own. His performances are highly-skilled physical achievements. Dufrêne was the author also of a lengthy and supreme example of lettriste or ultra-lettriste poetry, published in 1958, ‘Tombeau de Pierre Larousse’, in which he employs words, often proper names, ellided, strangely spelt, given unexpected accents, structured into rhythmical, textured sound patterns of subtlety and force.</p>

<p>With Dufrêne, the time taken to make a tape is the time taken to accomplish a performance (or little more than twice that time if superimposition is used). However a tape can take far longer. Henri Chopin speaks of ‘requiring for each work days and months’ of application and research, as ‘here all the authors are analysts of the language which they synthesize in their productions.’ He is alluding to his own practice and to that of such poets as Paul de Vree, Brion Gysin and Bernard Heidsieck.</p>

<p>Chopin began to work with tape in 1955, though his first really successful composition was not made until 1957. He at first employed the sounds, vowel and consonantal, of words, decomposing and recomposing them in the process. An early work was based upon the words ‘sol air’, recording the individual sounds, slowing them down or speeding them up, superimposing not once but up to fifty times, adding other sounds such as breathing effects and smackings of the lips, also slowed or speeded. In later pieces, Chopin abandonned words altogether and used only particles of vocal sound.</p>

<p>Over the years, he has explored more fully than anyone else these ‘micro-particles’ of the human voice, and has over them the utmost control. The sounds he makes are often almost imperceptible to the ear, but by amplifying, changing speeds and superimposing, one mouth becomes an orchestra. His ‘poésie sonore’, which he utterly distinguishes from ‘poésie phonétique’, is a fully worked out and expressive new language which frees him from the Word, which he regards as an impediment to living, an imposition upon life. His programme thus is both artistic and social-political.</p>

<p>Paul de Vree (Belgium) makes a similar point when he says that ‘all predication is an assault upon the freedom of man. Poetry as I conceive of it, is no longer the handmaiden of princes, prelates, politicians, parties, or even the people. It is at last itself.’</p>

<p>De Vree seems, in his audio-visual poems, at first more orthodox. For a start unlike Chopin’s poèmes sonores and Duf rêne’s cri-rhythmes, they can be written down. But one notices the reliance on sound to convey meaning, the subtle overtones and undertones, fantasies, nonsense words, echoes of the surreal world. De Vree then takes these texts and, in collaboration with a reciter and a composer or an engineer, he realises them in a performance on tape. ‘Actually all depends upon the new possibilities of mechanical expression.’ Using loops and repetitions, echo effects, reverberation and the like, he forges a delicately pointed and precise collaboration between the voice as concrete sound and the form and expressiveness of the original poem. The result is exciting and beautiful. But, he adds, ‘it goes without saying that the reciter (where it is not the poet) and the engineer of sounds have contributed personally to the originality of the realisation. The dawn of the era of electronic poetry is no longer a figment of the imagination.’ De Vree’s first audiovisual poem ‘Veronika’ dates from 1962. It was broadcast in 1963. The function of the machine treatment in many poems by De Vree, Brion Gysin and others is to intensify them and point their qualities, particularly their qualities of sound, to make the poems more like themselves.
Brion Gysin (Tangiers) is a permutational poet. A simple five-word phrase such as ‘I am that I am’ will produce up to 120 permutations of word order and thus of meaning. ‘Poets are meant to liberate words, not chain them in phrases. Who told poets they were supposed to think ? Poets are meant to sing and to make words sing.’ Gysin restores to words their substance and vitality. By the almost mathematical precision of his permutations he multiplies subtleties of meaning and establishes each word fully in the round. The text may then be further transformed by treatment on tape. ‘I am that I am’, with permutations, superimpositions, speedings and slowings, becomes in turn statement, question, affirmation, doubt, hysteria, negation, obliteration and slow climb back to selfestablishment. Gysin’s poems were first published and broadcast in 1960.</p>

<p>Bernard Heidsieck has been working in France, since 1955, first on a series of poèmes partitions and, since 1966, on his biopsies. He describes both as ‘action poetry’ because they incorporate actuality in the form of recordings of everyday sounds and events, and pre-existing, often topical, texts from newspapers and magazines. The action poem incorporates ‘anything that the poem authorises itself to take’ and, by superimposing various texts or strands of sound, manages to ‘arouse, to awaken other layers of sensibility’, and to deal with aspects of contemporary life in a satirical, humorous or probing way. It is a ‘ritual, ceremonial or event’ whose purpose is ‘to question our daily gestures and words and cries. To appropriate them or dynamite’them. To make them meaningful… to animate our mechanical and technocratic age by recapturing mystery and breath’. Heidsieck’s poetry is made on tape by ‘manipulations of speed, volume, superimposition, cutting and joining.’ Often the texts are rapidly and skilfully read in Heidsieck’s own voice, and the weaving of the strands gives a rich contrapuntal effect which can be appreciated as texture and expressionistic vocal music quite apart from the humour and satire of the disparate textual meanings.</p>

<p>Duf rêne, Wolman, Chopin, De Vree, Gysin and Heidsieck have all been published by Henri Chopin on the records accompanying issues of his magazine Cinquième Saison or, as it is now called, OU. This magazine has been the most important influence in propagating knowledge of concrete sound poetry throughout the world. It is joined now by another series of records published jointly in Sweden by Fylkingen and Sveriges Radio.
The first text-sound compositions in Sweden were by Öyvind Fahlström in 1961 and 1962. In 1964 and 1965, two poetcomposers, Bengt Emil Johnson and Lars-Gunnar Bodin began to work in the field of sound-texts. In 1967, the Fylkingen group concerned with linguistic arts collaborated with the literary section of Sveriges Radio to give several other poets a chance of working in this new area. The Electronic Music Studio of Sveriges Radio was made available to poets and work began in earnest. In 1968, 69 and 70, three festivals of text-sound compositions have been held in Stockholm. Altogether, sixteen Swedish poets and fifteen poets from abroad have been given the opportunity of making compositions for one or more of these festivals. A large proportion of these are included in the records which document the festivals.</p>

<p>Fylkingen, which began as a music organisation, gradually became interested in the other arts, especially from the point of view of the relationship between art and technology. Not only did Swedish sound poets have a fully equipped electronic music studio at their disposal, but several of them had the opportunity also of using computers and voice synthesizers. Calling their works text-sound compositions left them free to use other types of sound, including electronically generated effects. Stereo was common from the first and, since 1967,4-channel reproduction has almost become the rule, allowing sound to be placed, controlled and moved in space with the utmost precision.</p>

<p>Bengt Emil Johnson has been foremost in the search for new techniques of expression. In ‘Through the mirror of thirst’, fragments of one of his earlier poems have been randomly selected and, also on a chance basis, have been allocated to one of four voices; controlled as to density per time unit of 30 seconds; in speed, from very fast to very slow; spatial position on the four channels; type of electronic treatment, etc. In this way, within a basically semantic structure, small details of recorded text have been separated out and vividly exposed.</p>

<p>In another piece, Johnson uses a computer to effect a series of gradual transformations from one text to another; and for a third, produced also with the aid of a computer, a text of invented words which obey all the rules of Swedish wordconstruction and syntax was prepared. Lars-Gunnar Bodin has a musician’s attitude to his material. In ‘From any point to any other point’ the text has been modified and transformed electronically until the semantic meaning disappears and only the rhythmic structure of language remains. All that is left is a vestige of ‘oral behaviour’. This approach is appropriate in a work which discusses and reflects on scientific and technological views of the world.</p>

<p>The trend is taken still further by Christer Hennix Lille, also a composer, who in his ‘Still Life, CL<em>’ makes one of the first uses of synthetic speech in an artistic creation. The synthesizer’s computer unit is used to ‘generate parameters of articulation, so that malformations in syntax and pronunciation become a ‘value’ of the ‘local’ mutation frequency of the piece’. Q</em> is a ‘code’ which has reference to the behaviour of memory in language as related to the genetic code of the individual. In the future, many more works are likely to be realised with the aid of the synthesizer.</p>

<p>In theory, it will be possible to produce synthetically exactly the voice quality required as constituent material for any composition.</p>

<p>Sten Hanson makes use of the letters A C G and T, which are abbreviations for the names of the bases forming the genetic code, in his piece ‘La destruction de votre code génétique par drogues, toxines et irradiation.’ As the piece proceeds, the pronunciation of the letters is distorted and broken down by the introduction of ‘foreign’ sound elements produced in a purely electronic way. Hanson, in his smallscale works, uses advanced techniques for social-political ends.</p>

<p>Åke Hodell, after a number of very effective phonetic pieces, has produced large-scale works almost in the documentary mould. ‘USS Pacific Ocean’ is concerned with a dramatic, imagined political crisis; while ‘Where is Eldridge Cleaver ?’ is based on contemporary events in America. In this piece, 4-channel tape-recording is used effectively to give, for example, the sound of soldiers marching round and round the audience.</p>

<p>There is a danger, of course, that electronic and other effects will be used in a sterile way, but the Swedes, on the whole, seem to have avoided this. Johnson and Bodin, largely in musical terms, and Hanson and Hodell in social-political terms, have proved their ability to use effects to engage and implicate the listener. Often, there is a continous interplay between semantically meaningful portions and the resonant development of these, frequently in combination with other sounds. Form is a vehicle for content, and even the use of 4-channel reproduction is carried out in a way that illuminates the meaning of the composition.
There seem to be as many approaches as there are poets. Many others could be mentioned:</p>

<p>Ernst Jandl (Austria), the primary exponent, at the present time, of phonetic poetry for the unaided voice, who breaks words up into meaningful soundfragments, recomposes them, organises them with rhythmic and structural precision. (Even Jandl, though, has realised electronically some of his poems in collaboration with the British Broadcasting Corporation’s Radiophonic Workshop);</p>

<p>Ladislav Novak (Czechoslovakia), whose complex superimpositions of, often, a single sentence in Czech or Latin seem to be cries of freedom, in line with Franz Mon’s observation that spatially articulated language becomes effective at the point when ‘conventional language sanctioned by society reaches its limits, or for some reason may not be used’;</p>

<p>Frans Mon himself (West Germany), who has conducted a continuing study into the structure and method of language;</p>

<p>Gust Gils (Belgium) who uses vocal sounds without semantic meaning, seeing the sound poem as an opportunity for a poet whose native language has a limited audience to break out of his isolation;</p>

<p>Bengt af Klintberg (Sweden) whose work often contains elements of folklore, cusha-calls and incantation;</p>

<p>Svante Bodin (also Sweden) who has used the computer to scramble and transform a text in a number of valid ways;</p>

<p>and dozens more, in Sweden, Denmark, Finland, France, Belgium, The Netherlands, Germany, Italy, Czechoslovakia, U K, U S A, Canada, Japan, South America and elsewhere.</p>

<p>Two lines of development in concrete sound poetry seem to be complementary. One, the attempt to come to terms with scientific and technological development in order to enable man to continue to be at home in his world, the humanisation of the machine, the marrying of human warmth to the coldness of much electronically generated sound. The other, the return to the primitive, to incantation and ritual, to the coming together again of music and poetry, the amalgamation with movement and dance, the growth of the voice to its full physical powers again as part of the body, the body as language.</p>

<p>The very diversity of sound poetry is in line with its emphasis on the freedom of the individual and the withering of external authority, on man as a communal and social animal, on communication as a lifegiving activity, things which in this bureaucratic and technocratic age we need constantly to remember.</p>


</div>
</div>
	
	<script>
var coll = document.getElementsByClassName("collapsible-text-button");
var i;

for (i = 0; i < coll.length; i++) {
  coll[i].addEventListener("click", function() {
    this.classList.toggle("active");
    var container = this.parentElement;
    var content = this.nextElementSibling;
    if (content.style.maxHeight){
      content.style.maxHeight = null;
      container.classList.remove("expanded");
    } else {
      container.classList.add("expanded");
      content.style.maxHeight = content.scrollHeight + "px";
    } 
  });
}
</script>

	
	<h3>Explore the Catalogue</h3>
	
	<iframe src="https://archive.org/embed/klankteksten" width="100%" height="500" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen></iframe>
	
	<p><em>This is a preview only - <a href="https://archive.org/details/klankteksten" target="_blank">view fullsize on archive.org</a></em></p>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Vinyl LP</h2>
	
	

<table id="infobox">
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2">
                <a href="#" data-featherlight="/assets/articles/klankteksten/front.jpg"><img class="infobox-image" src="/assets/articles/klankteksten/front.jpg"></a>
            </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td colspan="2" id="infobox-subtitle"><cite>Sound Texts - Concrete Poetry - Visual Texts</cite></td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publisher</th>
            <td>Stedelijk Museum, Amsterdam</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Publishing date</th>
            <td>1970</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        <tr>
            <th scope="row">Format</th>
            <td>Vinyl</td>
        </tr>
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
    </tbody>
</table>

	
	<p>The exhibition catalogue came with a LP of concrete poetry recordings, supervised by Bob Cobbing.</p>
	
	<strong>Tracklisting:</strong>
	<ul>
		<li>A1. Henri Chopin - Espaces et gestes (4:50)</li>
		<li>A2. François Dufrêne - Crirythme pour Bob Cobbing (5:50)</li>
		<li>A3. Bernard Heidsieck - Chapeau (4:43)</li>
		<li>A4. Paul de Vree - Rivièra (3:05)</li>
		<li>A5. Paul de Vree - Het leven is een baccarat (1:20)</li>
		<li>B1. Bengt Emil Johnson - 5|1970 (Lecture on...) (4:50)</li>
		<li>B2. Sten Hanson - Subface (4:15)</li>
		<li>B3. Bob Cobbing - Variations on a Theme of Tan (6:55)</li>
		<li>B4. Ladislav Novák - Descartes' Metamorphosis into Liquid (3:00)</li>
		<li>B5. Ernst Jandl - Ode auf N (1:50)</li>
		<li>B6. Ernst Jandl - JEEEEEEEEEEEEEESUSS (1:50)</li>
	</ul>
	
	Dates of composition:
	<ul>
		<li>A1 - 1959</li>
		<li>A2 - 1970</li>
		<li>A3 - 1970</li>
		<li>A4 - 1967</li>
		<li>A5 - 1967</li>
		<li>B1 - 1970</li>
		<li>B2 - 1970</li>
		<li>B3 - 1964/1968</li>
		<li>B4 - 1968</li>
		<li>B5 - 1957</li>
		<li>B6 - 1966</li>
	</ul>
</section>

<section>
	<h2>Gallery</h2>
	
	<section
		data-featherlight-gallery
		data-featherlight-filter="a"
		class="gallery-grid"
		>
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_084.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_084.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Toshihiko Shimizu - <em>six meditations</em> (1969)</figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_092.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_092.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>John Furnival - <em>tower of pisa</em> (1966)</figcaption>
			</figure>
		
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_096.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_096.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>John Sharkey - <em>$ kill</em> (1969)</figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_116.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_116.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Mathias Goeritz - <em>oro</em> (1961)</figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_126.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_126.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Ladislav Nebesky - <em>elipsa-epilepsie</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
		
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_137.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_137.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Alain Arias Misson - <em>music box</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
			
			<figure>
				<a href="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_150.jpg"><img src="/assets/articles/klankteksten/klankteksten_150.jpg"></a>
				<figcaption>Jonathan Williams - <em>White only black only</em></figcaption>
			</figure>
	</section>
</section>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="klankteksten" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(Sound Texts - Concrete Poetry - Visual Texts) is the title of an exhibition catalogue released in conjunction with the exhibition 'Klankteksten?' at the Stedelijk Museum in Amsterdam, Netherlands in November 1970. The exhibition provided an overview of the concrete poetry movement.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/social_media/logo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>